<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached in the French church, in London on the 29. day of August 1652 At the imposition of hands on Mr. Stouppe by John Bulteel, minister of the word of God. With the action and circumstances thereof.</title>
            <author>J. B. (John Bulteel), d. 1669.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 109 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77792</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B5453A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R224358</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99896951</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99896951</idno>
            <idno type="VID">135682</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77792)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 135682)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2454:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached in the French church, in London on the 29. day of August 1652 At the imposition of hands on Mr. Stouppe by John Bulteel, minister of the word of God. With the action and circumstances thereof.</title>
                  <author>J. B. (John Bulteel), d. 1669.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 38 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by T.M. for Edward Archer, and are to be sold at the sign of the Adam and Eve in Little-Brittain, near the Church,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1654.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Imposition of hands --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:135682:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED In the <hi>FRENCH CHURCH,</hi> in LONDON On the 29. day of <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1652. At the Impoſition of Hands on <hi>Mr. Stouppe</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By JOHN BULTEEL, Miniſter of the Word of God.</p>
            <p>With the Action and Circumſtances thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T.M.</hi> for <hi>Edward Archer,</hi> and are to be ſold at the Sign of the <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> in <hi>Little-Brittain,</hi> near the Church. 1654.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:135682:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:135682:2"/>
            <head>To his Reverend and honoured Brethren, The Paſtors, Elders, and Deacons of the <hi>French</hi>-Church in <hi>London.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reverend and Honoured Brethren,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Ambaſſadour of the Emperour of <hi>Germany,</hi> who was ſent to the great Emperor of the Turks writes that he ſaw at <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople</hi> an Embleme re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented on a piece of Tape<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, made of an exquiſite work, containing four Candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticks with four Candles, which repreſented four ſorts of Religions; as namely, the Heatheniſh, the Jewiſh, the Chriſtian, and the Mahometan. Three of theſe candleſticks were turned topſie, turvie, with their three Candles extinguiſhed; but the fourth Candleſtick ſtood upright, with its Candle burning: There was this Arabicall Inſcription. <hi>This is the true Light,</hi> thinking to make to world to believe, that the Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metane Religion is the onely and true light; and that
<pb facs="tcp:135682:3"/>
the three other lights extinguiſhed are falſe ones. But we know that the Chriſtian Religion is the onely and true Light, repreſented and preſented, not in, nor by the books of the Philoſophers, nor in the Talmud and Cabala of the Rabbins, nor in the Alcoran of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humetans; but within and by the holy Scripture, which repreſents and preſents unto us, our Lord Jeſus Chriſt the true light, <hi>who lighteth every man that cometh into the world, that whoſoever believes in him and follows him, ſhall not walk in darkneſſe, but have the light of life. It is he that is in the midſt of the golden candleſticks, who hath in his right hand ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſtars; out of whoſe mouth iſſueth a ſharp two edged ſword, wherewith he ſmites the Nations, whoſe countenance is as the Sun-ſhine in his ſtrength.</hi> It is that Jeſus Chriſt the Son of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, who by his beams doth inlighten the ſtarres, who are the Angels of the Churches; it is he that walks amidſt the golden Candle ſticks, which are the Churches, and doth enlighten them by his holy word, which is a lamp unto their feet, and a lantern of light unto paſſengers in the dark nights on ſea, which doth enlighten them within the glittering rayes of his holy ſpirit. It is that divine word, that gliſtering light of the Old and New Teſtament, of the Law and of the Goſpel, carried by the Torch-bearers, the excellent and holy Prophets, Apoſtles, Evangeliſts, and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the word of God. But the world of unbelievers, whether Heathens, Hereticks, or Prophane perſons, hath not known nor received this marvellous light of this ſacred word, but hath rejected it, indeavoured to exinguiſh it, either in whole or in part.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:135682:3"/>The Pagans have rejected the holy Scripture altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. The Manichees have refuſed all the old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. The Ptolemaits have rejected the five books of <hi>Moſes,</hi> which the Sadduces did onely imbrace, refuſing all other books of the old Teſtament. The Anabaptiſts reject the book of <hi>Eccleſiaſtes,</hi> &amp; the canticle of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles. Porphyrius</hi> did refuſe the book of the Prophet <hi>Daniel,</hi> and the Nicolaitans did the like of the Pſalmes of the royall Prophet <hi>David.</hi> The Jews reject all the New Teſtament. The Ebionites have onely Saint <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thews</hi> Goſpel, and <hi>Cerinthus</hi> approved that of Saint <hi>Mark; Cerdon</hi> that of Saint <hi>Luke;</hi> the Valentini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans did onely imbrace that of Saint <hi>John,</hi> and the <hi>Tatians,</hi> onely the book of the <hi>Acts</hi> of the Apoſtles. Theſe are thoſe that have blot out the paſſages of holy Scripture, which were contrary to their opinions and practiſes. <hi>Mareion</hi> the Heretick did blot out the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages of Luke and <hi>John,</hi> and of the Apoſtles Epiſtles, that maintained the Deity and humanity of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt. The Papiſts do raze out many ſentences that repugne their falſe dogmes, and among others, the ſecond Commandement of the Morall Law. <hi>Thou ſhalt not make unto thee any graven image, &amp;c.</hi> is left out, as appears in many of their Printed books. But behold a ſtrange caſe, that among thoſe of the reformed Religion there are ſome here in <hi>England,</hi> that have cauſed ſome Paſſages of the holy Scripture to be razed out that were written on the walls of Churches. As for Example, there was a ſuffragant of the Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> who a little before theſe troubles did excommunicate two Churhwardens, becauſe they had not blotted out that notable and true
<pb facs="tcp:135682:4"/>
ſentence written on the wall of the Church (where he kept his Spirituall Court) <hi>My Houſe ſhall be called the Houſe of prayer, but ye have made it a den of thieves;</hi> yea there was at the ſame time a Biſhop in <hi>England,</hi> who cauſed the Clark of a Pariſh in his Dioceſſe, to blot out that Divine ſentence written on the wall, juſt right over the Miniſters pulpit. <hi>Neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is laid upon me, yea wo is unto me if I preach not the Goſpel.</hi> An inſupportable boldneſſe, and which cannot be paralelled, theſe perſons would in all appearance have indeavoured to have blotted theſe Divine Sentences out of the books of holy Scripture, if it had been in their power. <hi>Cumanus</hi> a Heathen Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour of the Romanes, cauſed a Romane Souldier to be beheaded: for tearing the books of <hi>Moſes,</hi> at the Sack of a city, to appeaſe the tumult of the Jews, who were ſcandaliſed thereat. Surely God ſaith in the <hi>Apocalipſe</hi> chap. <hi>22.19. If any man ſhall take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from the words of the book of this Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, God ſhall take away his part out of the Book of Life, and out of the holy City.</hi> Now whereas I have expounded in your Church the aforeſaid paſſage of the <hi>1 Corinth. 9.16. For though I preach the Goſpel, I have nothing to glory of, for neceſſity is laid upon me; yea wo is unto if I preach not the Goſpel.</hi> I do repreſent and preſent the Sermon unto you, becauſe it is due unto you, having been the occaſion thereof; for being requeſted by Letters ſigned by the Paſtor and ſome of the Elders and Deacons of your Church, in the name of them all, to come to <hi>London,</hi> to aſſiſt to the examination of the Honoured brother Mr. <hi>Stouppe,</hi> where divers reverend bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,
<pb facs="tcp:135682:4"/>
Miniſters did aſſiſt, with the Elders and Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons of the <hi>Coetus</hi> of the <hi>Dutch</hi> and <hi>French</hi> Churches of <hi>London;</hi> and having heard him both in his Sermon <hi>ad Clerum,</hi> and his Latine <hi>Theſes,</hi> as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in his Anſwers to what objections ſoever were pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded unto him; the company did receive ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment and ſatisfaction, as he was judged able and capable to be received and confirmed in the holy Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry. Yee did me the honor to requeſt me to preach and perform the Action on the day of his Ordination, at which aſſiſted the Reverend Brethren, Mr. <hi>Calen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drin</hi> Paſtor of the <hi>Dutch</hi> Church, and Mr. <hi>Ciſmer</hi> Paſtor of your Church: we all three together gave the Impoſition of hands on the ſaid honoured brother Mr. <hi>Stouppe.</hi> Now I put this Sermon in print, becauſe this Action of Impoſition of hands, hath been little fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent and uſed in your Church; for there are very near <hi>50</hi> years ſince, Mr. <hi>Aurelius,</hi> deceaſed ſon of an Italian was the laſt that received the Impoſition of hands, and was received Miniſter of your Church; the other Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors that came ſince, were miniſters, and the moſt part old ones, before they were Paſtors of your Church. Beſides there are Miniſters, eſpecially in <hi>France,</hi> who have cauſed their <hi>Sermons</hi> to be printed on occaſions of the like ſubject, and of the ſame na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Adde unto this, that there are many that could not be preſent at the Sermon, that will be glad to read that which they have not ſeen nor heard; and there are others that will be content to refreſh their memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries thereby. I have added here and there, and eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially that which concerns this Countrey and Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which the ſhortneſſe of time did not permit me to
<pb facs="tcp:135682:5"/>
publiſh in the Pulpit. I hope that I ſhall have the ſame liberty permitted unto me, which the worthy Engliſh Miniſters have had, that have preached before the Honorable Houſes of Parliament; ſetting forth to light that which they had conceived, and premeditated in their thoughts, which the brevity of time did not give them leaſure to preach; and that without any preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice either of the Chriſtian hearer or Reader, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with pleaſure and much profit, and have been both praiſed and thanked for it. As concerning the Impoſition or laying on of the hands, by us the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters that were preſent, on our ſaid brother; it is true, that <hi>France, Holland,</hi> and here among us, and elſewhere; it is ordinarily done by one Miniſter alone, where there are no other miniſters preſent, yea by one miniſter alone, although there are other miniſters pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, that give onely the right hand of fellowſhip to the miniſter confirmed. Notwithſtanding the Action of the Impoſition of hands is a thing indifferent in the opinion and judgement of many learned men, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther one miniſter, or many miniſters together do give the Impoſition of hands on that perſon that is recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved into the miniſtry, ſo that the practice of the one ought not nor cannot prejudice or condemn the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of the other. We have all three miniſters laid our hands on <hi>Mr. Stouppe. Certes</hi> one of the Councels of <hi>Carthage,</hi> did ordain that the miniſters preſent, ſhould lay hands on the head of the miniſter ordained; the which hath been practiſed at all times, yea and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Papiſts; and there are Acts of Parliament in <hi>England</hi> to that effect, in the time of King <hi>Edward</hi> the <hi>6.</hi> and of Queen <hi>Eliſabeth</hi> of happy memory, and
<pb facs="tcp:135682:5"/>
it is practiſed at preſent in <hi>London,</hi> among the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh miniſters; for the laying on of hands, is done by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers miniſters of the company of the Preſbytery. And indeed if we mount up higher, we ſhall find that that was practiſed in the Primitive Church, in the time of the Apoſtles, for it appears, that <hi>Saul</hi> or <hi>Paul</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the Impoſition of hands by many, <hi>Acts chap. 13.3.</hi> and the ſame Apoſtle writing of the Impoſition of hands given unto <hi>Timothy</hi> his own ſon in the faith, ſaith, <hi>Stir up the gift of God which is in thee by the putting on of my hands, 2</hi> Tim. <hi>1.6.</hi> but he had ſaid before. <hi>Neglect not the gift that is in thee, which was given thee by propheſie, with the laying on of the hands of the Presbytery, 1</hi> Tim. <hi>4.14.</hi> and notwithſtanding he makes mention in theſe two places of one ſame action, and of one ſame perſon, namely Timothy ordained and confirmed: <hi>Paul</hi> as he was an Apoſtle, being the primary and the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall in this action of the Impoſition of hands, with the others. But alas we have in theſe times in this Land, ſome that ſay they are inlightened, having found new Lights, who are notwithſtanding <hi>wandring ſtarres,</hi> as Saint <hi>Jude</hi> ſaith; who care neither for the laying on of hands, nor of the right hand of fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip; who as the Enthuſiaſts have revelations and viſions; and run and propheſie (as heretofore the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabaptiſts did) without any ordinary or extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary calling; taking a Priviledge above Jeſus Chriſt and <hi>Aaron, who took not that honour unto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, nor glorified themſelves, but were called of God,</hi> they are blind guides, and leaders of the blind, and if the blind lead the blind, both ſhall fall
<pb facs="tcp:135682:6"/>
into the ditch. God the Father of lights enlighten them, and tranſport them from darkneſſe to his mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellous light, transforming them by the renewing of their minds, that they may prove, what is that good, that acceptable and perfect will of God. I beſeech the ſame good God, that he will be pleaſed to ſtrengthen you in the knowledge, which he hath given you of his holy truth in his holyword, working in you both to will, and to do, of his good pleaſure, that ye may be without reproach and blameleſſe in the midſt of a crooked and perverſe generation, among whom ye ſhine as lights in the world, holding forth the word of life. This is the wiſh of him, who hopes ye will accept this ſmall preſent in good part, threreby ye will adde an obligation to the precedent obligations unto him who is and remains.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Reverend and Dear Brethren,</hi> Your moſt humble and moſt affectionate brother, and ſervant in the Lord, <hi>John Bulteel.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:135682:6"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>1 Cor. 9.16.</bibl>
                  <p>For though I preach the Goſpel, I have nothing to glory of, for neceſſity is laid upon me; yea wo is to me, if I preach not the Goſpel.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Lord gave a Commandement unto <hi>Moſes,</hi> to put into the Ark of the Covenant, the gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Pot that had Manna, <hi>Aarons</hi> rod, the tables of the Covenant, and the Cherubins of glory, ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowing the Mercy ſeat. The Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of the Law did repreſent the preaching of the Law; the Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rubims of glory ſhadowing the Mercy Seat, did ſhew forth the preaching of the Goſpel; the Manna did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the Sacraments; and the Rod of <hi>Aaron</hi> did ſignifie the Diſcipline. This Ark was carried by the Prieſts and Levites of the Law; no other among the Jews could nor ought to carry it, to ſhow that there are none but the Miniſters of God, that have authority to preach the word of God, either of the Law or of the Goſpel; to give the Sacraments, and exerciſe the Eccleſiaſticall diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline. It was a particular, honour unto the Prieſts and Levites, but it was alſo a burthen; and indeed the name of Prieſt in the holy language ſignifies a Prince and a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant. A Prince, there is Honor, a ſervant, there is ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice.
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:135682:7"/>
And that excellent Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> that veſſel of Election ſaith,<note n="a" place="margin">1 Tim. 3.1.</note> 
               <hi>This is a true ſaying, if any man deſire the office of a Biſhop he deſireth a good work,</hi> in ſaying, excellent, he denotes the dignity of the Charge, in qualifying it a work, he ſignifies the charge of the Dignity, an honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable labour. In the ſame place he deſcribes the duties of the Miniſters of God, and the qualities that they ought to have, in the ſeven firſt verſes of that Chapter.</p>
            <p>It is that which the Apoſtle propoundeth in the ninth Chapter of this firſt Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthians;</hi> he ſets forth unto us explicitly and implicitly, two ſorts of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors; The one ſort of Paſtors, are ſuch of whom an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Father ſpeakes, namely <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> there are many and there are few, many by name, but few in ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect: who have the charge to preach the Goſpel, but do not preach it;<note n="b" place="margin">Iſa. 65.10.</note> 
               <hi>They are watchmen that are blind,</hi> they are dumb dogs that cannot bark, as the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſtyles them; and therefore wo unto them becauſe they preach not the Goſpel, as the Apoſtle teacheth us covertly and implicitly, in this ſixteenth verſe of our Text. The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond ſort is of thoſe that are Paſtors, not onely by name but alſo in effect; whom the Apoſtle ſubdivides in two ranks, The one, that preach the Goſpel, <hi>but againſt their will, though the diſpenſation of the Goſpel is committed unto them,</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Cor. 9.17.</note> in the 17 verſe of this Chapter, as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Jonas,</hi> who preached the word of God to the Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nivites againſt his deſire, and as it were perforce. The others that do preach the Goſpel willingly; whom the Apoſtle doth again ſubdivide into two ranks. Such as do preach the Goſpel willingly and live of the Goſpel, <hi>for the labourer is worthy of his hire.</hi> and Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in the<note n="d" place="margin">1 Cor. 9.19.</note> 14 verſe of this chap. <hi>even ſo hath the Lord ordained that they which preach the Goſpel ſhould live of the Goſpel;</hi> So Saint <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> and the brethren of our Lord Jeſus, and the reſt of the Apoſtles, preaching the Goſpel have lived of the Goſpel, as the Apoſtle doth declare unto us openly in the beginning of this Chapter. The others that do preach
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:135682:7"/>
the Goſpel, notwithſtanding do not live of the Goſpel, as <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> among the <hi>Corinthians</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">1 Cor. 3.4.5, 6, 7.</note> 
               <hi>Have we not power to eat and to drink? have we not power to lead about a ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, a wife, as well as other Apoſtles, and as the brethren of the Lord and Cephas? or</hi> I <hi>onely and</hi> Barnabas <hi>have we not power to forbear working? Who goeth to Warfare at any time at his own Charges? who planteth a vineyard and eateth not of the fruit thereof? or who feedeth a flock and eateth not of the milk of the flock?</hi> &amp;c. Now S. <hi>Paul</hi> doth glory in regard of the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> becauſe he preached the Goſpel for nought, although he might have lawfully taken a Salary, which was due unto him, and according to the ordinance of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt: and therefore he glories not in reſpect of God, or in reſpect of the Apoſtles; but partly in reſpect of the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> partly againſt the falſe Apoſtles. He glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries not that he preached the Goſpel, but that he preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Goſpel <hi>gratis,</hi> for nothing; <hi>for it were better for him to dy, than that any man ſhould make his glorying void,</hi> as he ſaith in the verſe that precedes our Text. But for that he preacheth the Goſpel, he cannot, no more than he ought not to glory, as he teacheth us in this 16 verſe of our Text, which we have read unto you.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For though I preach the goſpel, I have nothing to glory of, for ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity is laid upon me, yea wo is unto me if I preach not the Goſpel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A notable and noble paſſage of Scripture, an excellent, emphaticall, and patheticall ſentence, wherein there is not a word but hath its weight; in the which, we are to conſider by Gods grace and aſſiſtance, theſe two points; the firſt is the duty, the office and exerciſe of the Apoſtle; which is to preach the Goſpel; for he ſaith, <hi>Although I preach the Goſpel.</hi> The ſecond point is, that the Apoſtle doth not glory in that he preacheth the Goſpel, and that for two reaſon, the firſt is, the neceſſity, <hi>for neceſſity is laid upon me.</hi> The ſecond is the threatning, <hi>Wo is unto me if I preach not the Goſpel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We will not ſtand here to repreſent unto you what the word <hi>Goſpel,</hi> and <hi>to preach the Goſpel,</hi> ſignifies; becauſe we have underſtood not long ago what this word ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:135682:8"/>
in the expounding of theſe words.<note n="f" place="margin">Gal. 1.8.</note> 
               <hi>Though we or an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel from heaven preach any other Goſpel unto you, than that which we have preached unto you, let him be accurſed.</hi> Onely we will obſerve, that the word <hi>Goſpel,</hi> is a Greek word, which in prophane Greek authors ſignifies,</p>
            <p>Firſt of all, <hi>good and happy news.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, it ſignifies, <hi>the ſacrifice, that they offered unto their gods, for the good news they had received,</hi> and that <hi>ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice</hi> was called <hi>Goſpel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, it ſignifies the Salary and reward, or the gift that was made unto him that brought the good news and that gift and Salary was called <hi>Goſpel.</hi> But in holy Scripture; the word <hi>Goſpel</hi> ſignifies by excellency the good news; and ſolemn publication, of<note n="g" place="margin">1 Tim. 3.16.</note> 
               <hi>the Son of God manifeſted in the fleſh, juſtified in the Spirit, ſeen of Angels, preached unto the Gentiles, believed on in the world, received up into glory.</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Apoc. 14.6.</note> 
               <hi>The everlaſting Goſpel,</hi> which hath been preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſince the fall of man in the beginning of the Creation; and ſhall laſt unto the end of the world. The Franciſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cans had invented and publiſhed a book full of horrible blaſphemies, which they named, the Goſpel of the holy Ghoſt, or the everlaſting Goſpel; ſaying, that the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel of Chriſt ſhould not laſt above fifty years. But the Book was refuted by <hi>Guiliemus de ſancto amore,</hi> condemned by the Pope and ſecretly burnt.</p>
            <p>Now the holy Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> did preach the Goſpel in <hi>Arabia,</hi> at <hi>Damaſcus,</hi> in <hi>Antioch</hi> at <hi>Cyprus,</hi> in <hi>Licaonia,</hi> at <hi>Lyſtra,</hi> at <hi>Piſidia,</hi> in <hi>Macedonia,</hi> at <hi>Athens,</hi> at <hi>Corinth,</hi> in <hi>Aſia,</hi> in <hi>Europe,</hi> at <hi>Troas,</hi> at <hi>Miletum,</hi> in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> at <hi>Rome,</hi> in <hi>Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>philia,</hi> at <hi>Pergamus,</hi> in <hi>Attalia,</hi> in <hi>Myſia,</hi> at <hi>Salanus,</hi> at <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phos,</hi> in <hi>Samothracia,</hi> at <hi>Neapolis,</hi> at <hi>Philippi,</hi> at <hi>Berea,</hi> at <hi>Theſſalonica,</hi> and other places.<note n="i" place="margin">Rom. 15.19.</note> 
               <hi>Through mighty ſignes and wonders, by the power of the ſpirit of God, ſo that from</hi> Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, <hi>and round about unto</hi> Illyricum, <hi>he fully preached the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel of Chriſt.</hi> The Apoſtle therefore preached the Goſpel of Chriſt, and that at all times, and in all places, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his Apoſtolicall charge, and laboured more abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly than all the Apoſtles<note n="k" place="margin">1 Cor. 15 10.</note>: <hi>Yet not he, but the grace of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:135682:8"/>
God which was in him.</hi> Now although he preached the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel in this manner, with ſo much labour and pains, he hath not wherein to glory, and that is the ſecond point that we have to obſerve; when he ſaith,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I have nothing to glory of.</hi> Although the Goſpel is an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent thing, and the preaching thereof an Honourable work; although I have preached the Goſpel, I have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to glory of; he glories indeed in many other things, in that he hath exerciſed his office to teach with a pure conſcience.<note n="l" place="margin">2 Cor. 1.12.</note> 
               <hi>For our rejoycing is this, the Teſtimony of our conſcience, that in ſimplicity and godly ſincerity, we have had our converſation in the world, and more abundantly to you ward.</hi> He glories in the hope of the Glory of God, and in his afflictions.<note n="m" place="margin">Rom. 5.2, 3.</note> 
               <hi>We rejoyce in hope of the glory of God, and not onely ſo, but we glory in tribulations alſo.</hi> He glories in his infirmities.<note n="n" place="margin">2 Cor. 12 5.</note> 
               <hi>Yet of my ſelf I will not glorie, but in mine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities.</hi> He glories in the Croſſe of Chriſt,<note n="o" place="margin">Gal. 6.19</note> 
               <hi>God forbid that I ſhould glory, ſave in the Croſſe of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt by whom the world is crucified unto me, and I unto the world,</hi> But we read not that he glories in that he preached thd. Goſpel; becauſe he did not ſeek his own Glory, nor the glory of men, but the glory of God.<note n="p" place="margin">Rom. 5.11.</note> 
               <hi>We joy in God, through our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> The Phariſees did love more the glory of men, than the glory of God; but the Apoſtle who had been a Phariſee, was no more one, and did not ſeek his own glory; but was an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, and ſervant of Jeſus Chriſt; did imitate his Maſter; who ſaid,<note n="q" place="margin">Joh. 8.50.59.</note> 
               <hi>I ſeek not mine own glory. If I honour my ſelf, my Honour is nothing;</hi> and Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith,<note n="r" place="margin">1 Theſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.6,</note> 
               <hi>nor of men ſought we glory, neither of you, nor yet of others. So we ſpeak not as pleaſing men, but God, which tryeth our hearts. We are your ſervants for Chriſts ſake, and we do not preach our ſelves, but the Lord Chriſt? he</hi>
               <note n="s" place="margin">Joh. 7.18.</note> 
               <hi>that ſpeaketh of himſelf ſeeketh his own glory, but he that ſeeketh his glory that ſent him, the ſame is true, and no unrighteouſneſſe is in him,</hi> ſaith Chriſt; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,<note n="t" place="margin">2 Cor. 5.12.</note> 
               <hi>we commend not our ſelves unto you, but give you occaſion to glory on our behalf, not being covetous of vainglory.</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">1 Cor. 35 6, 7.</note> 
               <hi>I have planted,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Paul</hi>) Apollo <hi>watered, but God gave
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:135682:9"/>
the increaſe, ſo then neither he that planteth any thing, nor he that watereth, but God that giveth the increaſe. Who then is</hi> Paul, <hi>and who is</hi> Apollo? <hi>but Miniſters by whom ye believed?</hi> The Apoſtle therefore had no other aim nor end, but the advancement of Gods glory, the Kingdome of Jeſus Chriſt, and the ſalvation of men: he was not ſwoln with ambition, nor deſirous of vain glory, but he endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red onely to cauſe the light of the Goſpel of the glory of Chriſt to ſhine: he did glory not in his parentage, nor in his riches, nor in his wiſdome, nor in his ſtrength, but in God; according as<note n="x" place="margin">Cor. 1.31.</note> it is written, <hi>He that glorieth, let him glory in the Lord.</hi> He might well glory that he was ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted,<note n="y" place="margin">Luk. 110.20.</note> 
               <hi>that his name was written in heaven,</hi> but although he preached the Goſpel he had nothing to glory of, and gives the firſt reaſon; ſaying, <hi>For neceſſity is laid upon me,</hi> to wit, <hi>to preach the Goſpel;</hi> that which I neceſſarily do, hath nothing of Apoſtolicall glorying; for neceſſity takes away all matter and occaſion of glory. Now this neceſſity is laid upon me, and therefore I have not wherein to glory.</p>
            <p>Where obſerve here, that the Apoſtle ſpeaks not here of a neceſſity of conſtraint; (as we ſpeak in the Schools) as if the Apoſtle did not preach the Goſpel willingly, but againſt his mind, and will: God forbid that we ſhould ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect any ſuch thing of our Apoſtle; who was not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ready and willing to preach Chriſt;<note n="z" place="margin">Act. 21.13.</note> but <hi>he was ready alſo to be bound, yea to dye at</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>for the name of the Lord Jeſus.</hi> And in this Chapter, here of our Text, he doth<note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 9.17, 18.</note> 
               <hi>it willingly</hi> and heartily; which appears, becauſe he preached the Goſpel <hi>without charge.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">1 Pet. 5.2</note> 
               <hi>Ye fed the flock of God, not by conſtraint but willingly, not for filthy lucre, but of a ready mind,</hi> as Saint <hi>Peter</hi> writes. Behold the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy courage of the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> as ſoon as he hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth<note n="a" place="margin">Iſa. 6.8.</note> 
               <hi>the voyce of the Lord, ſaying, whom ſhall I ſend, and who will go for us?</hi> he preſents and offers himſelf immediately, and ſaith, <hi>Here am I, ſend me.</hi> In like manner the Apoſtle<note n="b" place="margin">Rom. 15.15.</note> 
               <hi>was ready to preach the Goſpel, as much as in him was;</hi> for as ſoon as he hears the voyce of the Sonne of God thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:135682:9"/>
from heaven; he asks<note n="c" place="margin">Acts 9.6.</note> 
               <hi>trembling and aſtoniſhed; Lord, what wilt thou have me to do?</hi> and immediately ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ys the voyce of Chriſt; he ſpeaks freely in <hi>Damaſcus,</hi> c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founds the Jews, and confirms that Jeſus is the Chriſt; and therefore, <hi>O King</hi> Agrippa,<note n="d" place="margin">Acts 26.19.</note> 
               <hi>I was not diſobedient unto the heavenly viſion, but ſhewed unto them of</hi> Damaſcus, <hi>and at Jeruſalem, and throughout all the coaſts of Judea, and then to the Gentiles, that they ſhould repent, &amp;c.</hi> and therefore the Apoſtle did preach willingly and not by compulſion; he ſpeaks not of a neceſſity of coaction, but he ſpeaks of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther neceſſity. This neceſſity is twofold; the one in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the people, and the other in regard of himſelf.</p>
            <p>Firſt of all, in regard of the people; for it was neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry that the Apoſtle ſhould preach the Goſpel unto the people of God; becauſe that the Miniſtry of Gods word is ſo neceſſary, that the ſaviour of the world ſaith<note n="e" place="margin">Luke 10.42.</note> 
               <hi>One thing is needfull.</hi> And the wiſe King <hi>Salomon</hi> foretelleth;<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 29.18.</note> 
               <hi>Where there is no viſion the people periſh,</hi> and there is no light of the ſunne, nor meat nor drink, ſo neceſſary to foment and nouriſh this animal and corruptible life; as the miniſtry of the Apoſtles and Paſtors, is to preſerve the Church of God, and to foment and cheriſh it with the word of God, which is the ſpirituall food of our ſouls.</p>
            <p>The ſecond neceſſity is in regard of himſelf, in as much as he was an Apoſtle; for neceſſity was laid upon him to preach, which was in reſpect of the neceſſity of obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and that was double.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In regard of the Commandement of God, for God had called <hi>Paul</hi> to the Apoſtleſhip, and had commanded him to preach,<note n="h" place="margin">Rom. 1.1</note> 
               <hi>Paul was called to be an Apoſtle ſeparated unto the Goſpel of God</hi> and as it is ſaid of the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah,</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Jer. 1.5.</note> 
               <hi>Before I formed thee in the belly, I knew thee; and before thou cameſt forth of the womb I ſanctified thee, and I ordained thee a Prophet unto the Nations.</hi> So the Apoſtle tells us of himſelf.<note n="k" place="margin">Gal. 1.15 16.</note> 
               <hi>When it pleaſed God, who ſeparated me from my Mothers womb, and called me by his grace to reveal his ſon in me, that I might preach him among the Heathen.</hi> And Cſtriſt calls unto <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Acts 26.16, 17.</note> 
               <hi>riſe &amp; ſtand upon thy feet, for I have appeared unto thee for this purpoſe, to make thee a miniſter and a witneſſe both of theſe
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:135682:10"/>
things which thou haſt ſeen and of thoſe things in the which I will appear unto thee; delivering thee from the people, and from the Gentiles, unto whom now I ſend thee.</hi> And therefore<note n="m" place="margin">Amos 3.8.</note> 
               <hi>The Lion hath roared, who will not fear? The Lord God hath ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, who can but propheſie?</hi> Amaziah <hi>the Prief of</hi> Bethel <hi>ſaid,</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Amos 7.12, 13, 14, 15.</note> 
               <hi>unto</hi> Amos; <hi>O thou Seer, go flee thee away into the Land of</hi> Judah, <hi>and there eat bread, and propheſie there; but propheſie not again any more at</hi> Bethel; <hi>for it is the Kings Chappel, and it is the Kings Court. Then anſwered</hi> Amos <hi>and ſaid to</hi> Ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ziah, <hi>I was no Prophet, neither was I a Prophets ſon, but I was an herdman, and a gatherer of Sycomore fruit; and the Lord took me as I followed the flock, and the Lord ſaid unto me, go pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie unto my people Iſrael.</hi> As if <hi>Amos</hi> had ſaid, I did not heretofore propheſie, but now I do propheſie, for there is a neceſſity laid upon me to propheſie. So Saint <hi>Paul</hi> was neither an Apoſtle, nor an Apoſtles ſon, but a Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſee, and a perſecutor of the Apoſtles, and diſciples of Chriſt, and of his Church; but after he received a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement from Chriſt, <hi>Go, I do ordain thee a miniſter of the Gentiles:</hi> this neceſſity was laid upon him to preach the Goſpel. This neceſſity of Gods command did make <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> to teach the people of the Jews, although he was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dopted ſon of the daughter of <hi>Pharaoh.</hi> It was this that induced the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> to propheſie, although rich, and noble, being the uncle unto the King <hi>Manaſſes</hi> (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the opinion of the <hi>Hebrews</hi>) So likewiſe <hi>Paul</hi> though an <hi>Hebrew</hi> of the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> of the tribe of <hi>Benja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min,</hi> a Phariſee as touching the Law, brought up at the feet of <hi>Gamaliel,</hi> did preach; for the neceſſity of Gods Command occaſioned the neceſſity of obligation: Saint <hi>Paul</hi> was obliged by the Commandment of God to preach the Goſpel, without any glorying therein;<note n="o" place="margin">Luke 17.10.</note> 
               <hi>When ye ſhall have done all thoſe things which are commanded, you ſay, we are unprofitable ſervants, we have done that which was our duty to do,</hi> ſaith Chriſt the Saviour of the world unto his Diſciples.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> was bound to preach the Goſpel by his calling, for his office, and thoſe excellent and eminent ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:135682:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
of his vocation did oblige him to do it, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, the Apoſtles, the Evangeliſts, and Miniſters of the word of God, are ſtiled <hi>the Chariots of Iſrael, and the horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men thereof; Angels, watchmen, Biſhops, overſeers, ſuperin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendants, fiſhers of men, the light and ſalt of the earth, workers and labourers, yea labourers together with God, builders, vine-dreſſers, Paſtors, ſpirituall Fathers, Stewards of the myſteries of God, ſaviours, ſtarres in the right hand of Chriſt;</hi> and other ſuch titles and admirable names that are attributed and appropriated unto them in holy ſcripture; to ſhew and ſignifie their calling, their charge, their duty, and their honour. We read that <hi>Timotheus</hi> the Muſician was ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pert, learned and admirable in his art; that he made of men, Lions or Lambs, when he would; for playing on his inſtrument, he did ſo ſtir up and encourage <hi>Alexander</hi> the great, that he did arm himſelf with all his armour, ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated and provoked with courage, and force to go and fight againſt his enemies, and then on a ſudden changing the tune and notes, he touched ſo ſweetly on the ſtrings of his inſtrument, that he did pacifie and mollifie King <hi>Alexander,</hi> he did calm him and made him as ſupple and quiet as a Lamb. The Miniſters of God are intitled <hi>Boa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerges, which is the ſons of thunder, Mark</hi> 3.17. who ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate and encourage the faithfull<note n="p" place="margin">Eph. 6 19 15, 16, 17.</note> 
               <hi>to take the whole armour of God, having their loins girt about with t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ruth, and having on the breaſt plate of righteouſneſſe, their feet ſhod with the prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Goſpel of peace, above all taking the ſhield of faith, and the helmet of ſalvation, and the ſword of the ſpirit, which is the word of God.</hi> By theſe heavenly weapons they fight a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Devil, the world, and the fleſh, and have the victory over them. They are beſides in another conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration ſtiled <hi>Boanerges the ſons of thunder,</hi> to thunder the Judgements of God againſt ſinners, and to draw them to repentance and humility, and to reclaim them, and make them as tame, &amp; quiet as lambs. The miniſters are alſo na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Barnabas (which is being interpreted the ſon of conſolation,</hi> Act. 4.36. to comfort all that mourn)<note n="q" place="margin">Iſa. 61.1.</note> 
               <hi>to preach good tidings unto the meek, to bind up the broken hearted, to proclaim liberty to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:135682:11"/>
the Captives, and the opening of the priſon to them that are bound.</hi> They are ſtiled <hi>Barſabas,</hi> Acts 1.23. to wit ſons of Converſion, converting ſinnes to repentance, yea and they are called <hi>Bar-jonas</hi> ſons of the dove, that is to ſay, ſons of peace and reconciliation. So that theſe titles which are given them do ſhew their Office and duty, their honor and charge, for it is not an idle dignity, but a work and honourable burden. Thus in the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment<note n="r" place="margin">Habbak. 1 1.</note> 
               <hi>The burden which Habbakuck the Prophet did ſee,</hi> and Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in the new Teſtament calls it<note n="ſ" place="margin">Rom. 1.5.</note> 
               <hi>grace and Apoſtle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi> or charge of Apoſtle. Now theſe titles above menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned did appertain unto <hi>Paul</hi> as an apoſtle and Evangeliſt, to repreſent his vocation, office, obligation, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore neceſſity was laid upon him to preach the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>But beſides this twofold neceſſity; there was another neceſſity that did preſſe and urge him, namely the threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and curſe of the Lord, in caſe he ſhewed himſelf re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fractory, and diſobedient and would not preach the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, and that is that which the Apoſtle propoundeth in the laſt place, which he ſaith,
<q>Yea wo is unto me, if I preach not the Goſpel.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Here we muſt obſerve that the word <hi>Wo</hi> is taken in holy Writ two manner of wayes.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It doth ſignifie a corporall wo, a temporall curſe, calamity and miſery.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A ſpirituall and everlaſting wo and curſe. When Jeſus Chriſt ſaid,<note n="u" place="margin">Mat. 24.19.</note> 
               <hi>Wo unto them that are with child, and to them that give ſuck in thoſe dayes;</hi> he ſpeaks not there of a ſpirituall and eternall wo, but of a temporall and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall wo, whereunto women that are with child and that give ſuck, ſhall be ſubject in thoſe times. But when he ſaith,<note n="x" place="margin">Luk. 6.25</note> 
               <hi>Wo unto you that are rich, for ye have received your conſolation, &amp;c.</hi> He ſpeaks of a ſpirituall and everlaſting wo: ſo the rich man that had had here on earth his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation, was in eternall deſolation and miſery in hell. For<note n="y" place="margin">Luk. 16.5.</note> Abraham <hi>ſaid unto him, ſon, remember that thou in thy life time received good things, &amp; likewiſe</hi> Lazarus <hi>evil things; but now he is comforted and thou art tormented.</hi> And the Reprobates do
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:135682:11"/>
feel in hell unſpeakable torments, which eye hath never ſeen, nor ear heard, neither hath entred into the heart of man, crying out unceſſantly, <hi>Wo, wo unto us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now when the Apoſtle ſaith here, <hi>wo is unto me,</hi> he means it not in the firſt ſenſe, he ſpeaks not of a tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall and corporall wo; he would and ſhould rather have ſaid in that ſenſe, wo is unto me that I preach the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, and happy ſhould I be, if I did not preach the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, for the apoſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e becauſe of the preaching of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, was in temporall miſery, in afflictions, in tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, in perſecution in priſon, wipped, ſtoned, and in extreme danger of death. The prophet <hi>Jeremiah</hi> cryes out<note n="z" place="margin">Jer. 15.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Wo is me my mother, that thou haſt born me a man of ſtrife, and a man of contention to the whole earth,</hi> and elſewhere he ſaith, <hi>I</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Jer. 20.7.8</note> 
               <hi>am in deriſion daily, every one mocketh me, for ſince I ſpake I cryed out, I cryed violence and ſpoil, becauſe the word of the Lord was made a reproach unto me, and a deriſion daily.</hi> Even ſo the Apoſtle might very well ſay of himſelf; wo unto me that I preach the Goſpel, for I am eſteemed a man of ſtrife for the Goſpels ſake,<note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 9.9 13.</note> 
               <hi>We are made a ſpecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle unto the world, unto Angels and to men, we are made as the filth of the world, and are become the off-ſcouring of all things unto this day.</hi> The Apoſtle therefore takes not this word wo in this ſenſe; but he means firſt and principally of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall and eternall wo; everlaſting damnation and death hangs over my head, if I preach not the Goſpel, and this neceſſity is impoſed on him if he will not incur eternall death, therefore he addes in this ninth chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of our Text, <hi>Leaſt by any means when I have preached to others, I my ſelf ſhould be a caſt away.</hi> And elſe where,<note n="b" place="margin">2 Cor. 13.6.</note> 
               <hi>I truſt that ye ſhall know that we are not reprobates.</hi> And therefore he exhorts his diſciple <hi>Timothy,</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">1 Tim. 4, 16.</note> 
               <hi>Take heed unto thy ſelf and unto the doctrine, continue in them, for in doing this, thou ſhalt both ſave thy ſelf, and them that hear thee.</hi> It is not to ſay, that Paſtors are the ſaviours of men, but God doth uſe and imploy their miniſtry to ſave them; they are like the finger of Saint <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> ſhewing them Chriſt, and ſaying, <hi>Behold the Lamb of God which taketh away
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:135682:12"/>
the ſins of the world.</hi> Or like unto thoſe that brought unto Jeſus Chriſt the blind or lunatick, or that had the pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, or poſſeſſed with Devils, or ſuch like, that he might heal them. Now the word of God threatens thoſe ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herds that do not their duty, nor execute their office,<note n="c" place="margin">Ezech. 39 2.</note> 
               <hi>Wo be to the ſhepherds of Iſrael that do feed themſelves; ſhould not the ſheperds feed their flocks?</hi> in like manner the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Jeremiah</hi> ſpeaks in the name of the Lord,<note n="e" place="margin">Jer. 23.1.</note> 
               <hi>Wo unto the Paſtors that deſtroy and ſcatter the ſheep of my Paſture</hi> (ſaith the Lord) and our Lord Jeſus Chriſt did pronounce the ſentence of wo againſt the Scribes, Phariſees, and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors of the Law;<note n="f" place="margin">Mat. 23.13, 16.</note> 
               <hi>Wo unto Scribes and Phariſees, Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites, for ye ſhut up the Kingdome of heaven againſt men, for ye neither go in your ſelves, neither ſuffer them that are entring to go in,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Wo unto you blind guides.</hi> It is not therefore with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ground and reaſon that the Apoſtle ſaith here, wo unto me, if I preach not the Goſpel of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Obſerve again, that the Apoſtle ſaith here, if I preach not the Goſpel; he ſayes not if I preach not the traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Phariſees, the ceremonies of the Jews, the injunctions of men, or the Statutes of Princes, but the Goſpel which Jeſus Chriſt hath preached and command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and therefore not another Goſpel, it is not to ſay that there is another Goſpel, another Jeſus, another ſpirit, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.4. (for there is but one true Chriſt, one true Goſpel, to ſpeak properly) but it is<note n="g" place="margin">Gal. 1.7.</note> 
               <hi>a perverting of the Goſpel of Chriſt,</hi> as we call the falſe Church, a Church but abuſively, and clear from the right uſe and ſenſe; now as wo is unto him if he preacheth not the Goſpel, ſo wo is unto him if he preach another Goſpel than the Goſpel of Chriſt. Therefore the Apoſtle proteſts<note n="h" place="margin">Acts 20.27.</note> 
               <hi>That he hath not ſhunned to declare all the Councel of God, and that he had received of the Lord that which he had delivered unto them,</hi> 1 Cor. 11.23. not mans tradition in lieu of Gods commandements (as Chriſt reproaches the Phariſees) but teaching and obſerving all that was commanded to the Apoſtles to keep and teach, according to this comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith,<note n="i" place="margin">1 Pet. 9.1.</note> 
               <hi>If any man ſpeak, let him ſpeak
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:135682:12"/>
as the oracles of God:</hi> this was repreſented by <hi>Aaron</hi> who had round about the hem of his garment bells of gold and pomegranates between them, <hi>Exod.</hi> 28.33. the ſound of the bells ſignified the preaching and that divine and excellent harmony of the true and pure Doctrine of the word. And <hi>certes,</hi> Paſtors are the Ambaſſadours of God. Now as an Ambaſſadour of a King dares not advance any thing of his own, nor exceed or go beyond his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion; but governs himſelf according to his commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and preſcriptions that are given him in writing by him that ſends him. Even ſo the Miniſters of the Goſpel who are the Ambaſſadours of the great God, do in like manner. The voyce of God ſaith unto <hi>Iſaiah</hi> the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet,<note n="k" place="margin">Iſa. 90.6.</note> 
               <hi>Cry;</hi> he dares not notwithſtanding cry of his own head, or put forth his own intention, his own inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but he ſaith unto God, <hi>What ſhall I cry?</hi> then the voyce doth ſuggeſt unto him the matter and ſubject of the cry; thence it came to paſſe that he was accuſtomed to cloſe all his propheſies with this ſentence, as he ſaith in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent fifth verſe of that chapter, for the mouth of the Lord hath ſpoken it. <q>
                  <note n="l" place="margin">Iſa. 1.7.9.</note>The Lord ſaith unto <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> whatſoever I command thee, that thou ſhalt ſpeak, and the Lord put forth his hand, and touched his mouth, and the Lord ſaid unto him, behold, I put my word in thy mouth.</q> It is that which the Prophet <hi>Ezeki<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el</hi> repreſents unto us, what God ſpeaks unto him, ſaying; <q>
                  <note n="m" place="margin">Ezech. 3.1, 2, 3.</note>Son of man eat this roll, and ſpeak to the houſe of Iſrael; then I did eat it, then he ſaid, go, get thee unto the houſe of Iſrael, and ſpeak with my words un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, giving to underſtand thereby, that his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſies were a recitall of the words contained in the roll, which was given him to eat; according to which the Prophets ordinarily began their propheſie.</q> 
               <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord, and the mouth of the Lord hath ſpoken it:</hi> To give us to underſtand, that the Prophets, Apoſtles, and Paſtors, ought not to teach or preach any thing, but the word and will of God; for if they propheſie, teach or preach any thing but the word of God and the Goſpel of Chriſt; wo will befall them.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:135682:13"/>Theſe things being thus briefly expounded, it remains that we apply them unto our ſelves, to our uſe, and for our inſtruction.</p>
            <p>From hence we have an uſe of redargution; for this Doctrine condemns thoſe of whom <hi>Gregory</hi> ſpeaks, the world is full of prieſts, and notwithſtanding, there are found but few Labourers in the harveſt; they take upon them the office, but do not execute the charge, they leave the charge, the preaching and the office, and take the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice and benefit thereof, ſuch are Archbiſhops, Cardinals, and Biſhops among the Papiſts; we may alſo ſay, ſome of our Biſhops, and ſome of our Miniſters of the word of God among us in this Land, who eſteem nothing in this world more unworthy of their perſons, than the charge of teaching; and ſeems unto them that it is a thing too low, contemptible and inferiour unto the Epiſcopal and Miniſteriall dignity, to preach the Goſpel, and notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding they do poſſeſſe and enjoy great Benefices and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venews. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith here, wo is unto me if I preach not the Goſpel, but they ſay clean contrary, wo unto us if we do preach the Goſpel. The Apoſtles ſaid, <q>
                  <note n="n" place="margin">Act. 6.2.9</note>It is not reaſonable, that we ſhould leave the word of God, and ſerve Tables; but we will give our ſelves continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to prayer, and to the Miniſtry of the word.</q> But the Popes, Cardinalls, Archbiſhops, Biſhops, in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary ſenſe do the quite contrary, it ſeems unto them that it is not reaſonable, that they ſhould leave the politick affairs of the State to preach the word; they eſteem it to be a baſe and vile thing to preach the Goſpel, whereas<note n="o" place="margin">Pet. 1.12.</note> 
               <hi>the angels themſelves deſired look into it,</hi> to ſearch and know the depth, and the bottome of this profound myſtery of the Goſpel, yea they were joyfull and ready to preach the birth of Chriſt<note n="p" place="margin">Luk. 2.10 13, 14.</note>; <q>Behold I bring you tidings of great joy, and with the angel there was a multitude of the heavenly hoſt, praiſing God and ſaying, glory to God in the higheſt, and earth Peace, good will tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards men.</q> The charge of the Miniſtry is ſo honorable, the burden ſo heavy (ſaith <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi>) that it is formi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:135682:13"/>
unto the angels, that the Angels themſelves not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, would eſteem it an honour, and would crouch and ſtoop their ſhoulders to bear it; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, how noble, how rich, how honorable ſoever men are let them not think that the Miniſtry is too vile or unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of them, but rather that they are unworthy of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry, as it appears by the forementioned and forenamed titles; for they are fellow ſervants with the angels, yea they are ſtiled angels; yea to which of the angels, unto w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> of the Princes of the world, did God at any time time ſay, that which he ſaid unto his apoſtles &amp; miniſters?<note n="q" place="margin">Mat. 16.19.</note> 
               <hi>whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver you ſhall bind on Earth, ſhall be bound in Heaven, Whatſoever you ſhall looſe on Earth, ſhall be looſed in Heaven.</hi> And<note n="r" place="margin">John 20.23.</note> 
               <hi>whoſe ſoever ſins yee remit they are remitted unto them, and whoſe ſoever ſinnes ye retain they are retained.</hi> But if the Cardinals, Archbiſhops and Biſhops of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church do preach, it is but rarely and ſeldome; and when they preach and teach, they do not preach the word of God, but falſe doctrine, the traditions of men; the ſuperſtitious cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of the Pope; they feed the people with Fables, and curious Queſtions; ſo that in what manner ſoever we do conſider them they are ranked and comprehended within and under the curſe, <hi>Wo unto them becauſe they preach not the Goſpel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. This condemns thoſe that ſwell and raiſe up them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves againſt God and againſt his Church, by oftentation, ambition or vain glory; a vice altogether unworthy of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, and Miniſters of Gods word, and notwithſtanding a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon vice, but a dangerous one; ſo that it is a ſafer thing to hear the word of God than to preach it; for he that hears Gods word learns to humble himſelf, but he that preaches, is in danger to exalt himſelf; for the more he receives the graces of God, the more he is ſubject to am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, and certes we ſee, that the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> was in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to exalt himſelf above meaſure, in that he was an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, <q>
                  <note n="ſ" place="margin">2 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 4.7</note> And through the abundance of the revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, caught up to the third heaven into Paradiſe, heard unſpeakable words, which is not lawfull or poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for a man to utter; there was given unto me a thorn
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:135682:14"/>
in the fleſh, the Mſſenger of Satan to buffet me, leſt I ſhould be exalted above meaſure.</q> Pirncipally this ſin is incident to novices and young miniſters<note n="t" place="margin">1 Tim. 3.6</note> 
               <hi>who are in danger to be lifted up with pride, and to fall into the condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Devil;</hi> as if he ſhould have ſaid, he will glory in that he is a miniſter,<note n="u" place="margin">Mat. 7.22.</note> and preacheth; <hi>Lord, Lord, have we not propheſied in thy name?</hi> O we muſt not glory in that, for though I preach the Goſpel (ſaith Saint <hi>Paul</hi>) I have nothing to glory of. If Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> ſo great, ſo excellent an Apoſtle, could not glory in that; who in all his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtles abaſeth himſelf, that God may be his all, and may be thereby exalted and glorified, who will know nothing, ſave Jeſus Chriſt, and him crucified; who proteſts that he will glory, not in his vertues, not in his merits, but in his infirmities, that the power of God may reſt upon him. If ſuch an Apoſtle ſo ſenſible of his infirmities, ſo humble by reaſon of them, ſuch an Herald of the mercy of God, ſuch an enemy of the merits of men, ſuch a trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peter of their ſinnes and demorits, if ſuch an Apoſtle could not, would not boaſt of ſuch things, and eſpecially would not glory in the preaching of the Goſpel, becauſe neceſſity was laid upon him, and wo unto him if he did not preach it: how much leſſe the Paſtors and miniſters of the word of God, inferiors to ſo great an Apoſtle, have they matter and occaſion to glory therein? by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of that neceſſity and of that threatning.</p>
            <p>But to come nearer unto our ſelves, and to apply thoſe things and uſes to us that are Paſtors, and to the brother whom we are to eſtabliſh and ordain unto the holy mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry, (without making a particular application unto our ſaid brother, as we might) We learn, and he alſo, our duty, which is propoſed at length in this 9. chapter of the 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> and in the firſt of <hi>Timothy</hi> chap. 3. and in firſt chapter of <hi>Titus,</hi> which we will read to you anon.</p>
            <p>The firſt and principall duty is to preach the Goſpel, and teach the truth, and will of God contained and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed in the ſacred Scripture,<note n="x" place="margin">2 Tim. 3.16, 17.</note> 
               <hi>Given by inſpiration of God, and profitable for doctrine, for reproof, for correction, for inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:135682:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
in righteouſneſſe; that the man of God may be perfect, throughly furniſhed unto oll good works,</hi> ſufficient not onely for our ſalvation, which the Papiſts confeſſe, but alſo for our inſtruction which they deny; witneſſe <hi>Bonner,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> who examining a martyr and telling him that he was a right Scripture man, and would have nothing but Scripture; and his Chaplain, who ſaid that he would have nothing, but his little pretty Gods book. And is it not ſufficient ſaid the martyr for our ſalvation, yes ſaid he it is ſufficient for our ſalvation, but not for our inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: O replyed the martyr, God ſend me the ſalvation, and you the inſtruction; and truly if it be ſufficient for the one, it is alſo for the other; for in the 13<hi rend="sup">th</hi> v. of the ſame chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, it is able to make thee wiſe unto ſalvation, and that not onely the man of God, the miniſter, the Doctor; but alſo the ſimple, the ignorant; it maketh wiſe the ſimple, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.8. for if it appertains onely to the learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and wiſe to read the Scriptures, it appertaineth to none; for no body is learned and wiſe before he hath read the holy ſcripture: We read not the word of God becauſe we are learned and wiſe, but to become ſo. It is that holy ſcripture, which is ſtiled a long Epiſtle, which the Creator ſends to the creature; the Teſtament of God the ſon, and the Library of God the holy Ghoſt; the book of the love of God; the mirror of mans miſerie, and of divine grace, the rich treaſury of the King of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry (wherein the ſpirituall manna and the water of life are to be found) the Arſenall and Armoury of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, a ſword with two edges, a touchſtone of truth, a lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern to our feet, and an anchor in the time of tempeſt yea, the ſacred Scripture is called a Paradiſe; <hi>God</hi> (ſaith <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe) walked of old in Paradiſe, and now God walketh in Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe, when I read the ſacred Scripture,</hi> Geneſis <hi>is a Paradiſe,</hi> Deuteronomy <hi>is a Paradiſe,</hi> the Goſpel is a Paradiſe unto me, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and truly well may it be called a Paradiſe, for the faithfull cannot find a pleaſanter place than in the Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe of holy Scripture, where the tree of knowledge is, not that was forbidden, but that which is appointed of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:135682:15"/>
God for the elect; where ſtandeth in the mids thereof, the tree of life w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> is Chriſt, the door whereof is not kept by Cherubims with the fiery ſword, but is opened unto all that are hungry; there are the rivers of lively waters to refreſh thoſe that are a thirſty, there are trees planted by God, that is, the Patriarks, prophets and Apoſtles, where the aire is calm; the ſweet aire and refreſhing breathing of the Holy Ghoſt; it is there where the voice of God is heard, not calling <hi>Adam</hi> where art thou, but inviting all ſinners unto him, <hi>Come unto me all ye that labour and are heavy laden, and I will give you reſt,</hi> leading them directly unto the tree of Life, refreſhing them and comforting them. The Garden of <hi>Eden</hi> out of the which <hi>Adam</hi> was thruſt forth, had but the ſhadow of the true, ſolide, and ſweet pleaſures which the faithfull do enjoy in this Garden of holy Scripture, wherein they hear the voice of God, ſee the apparition of Angels, are converſant with the holy Patriarks, and Prophets, and Apoſtles, yea with Chriſt himſelf, and do feed with great delight on the fruit of the tree of Life; and therefore let us con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent our ſelves with this Paradiſe, and contain our ſelves within the limits and cloſe of the holy Scripture, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out going for h out of it.</p>
            <p>Again the ſacred Scripture is compared unto a Map, containing a deſcription of the place of our ſojourning here in this vale of miſery, of our journey towards our heavenly Jeruſalem, containing all things neceſſary for us in this our pilgrimage, both for our inſtruction and proviſion, as alſo for our ſalvation. Beyond this ſacred Scripture, and without the Map thereof, there are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but uncertain and unknown things. The Coſmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graphers who deſcribe the world, are wont to place in the lower moſt part of their Maps, the far diſtant Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and unknown unto them, theſe words, <hi>Terra incog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nita,</hi> and ſay beyond theſe Countries are nothing but wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſes of ſand, without water, full of foul, wild and venomous beaſts, or ponds of unnavigable mud, or <hi>Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thia</hi> unhabited for cold. So beyond the ſacred Scriptures,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:135682:15"/>
there are nothing but unknown Lands, deſarts full of ſands of humane traditions, ſtinking pools, cruell and venomous beaſts, that is to ſay, of falſe opinions, and deteſtable hereſies, unknown and doubtfull wayes. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond this holy Scripture, there is nothing, but <hi>Scriptura incognita,</hi> the unknown Scripture, and unwritten word dangerous gulphs, where the anchor of our faith can take no hold, where all our ſounding plummets are too ſhort, and cannot ſound the bottome thereof, and where we muſt of neceſſity make ſhipwrack of our faith; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we muſt of neceſſity keep our ſelves within the M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>p of the holy Scripture, the Sea-mans compaſſe, the rule of ſobriety, the bridle of our diſcourſe, the limit of our faith, leſt we be toſſed and caſt upon ſome unknown coaſt and ſo periſh; we reſt our ſelves in the haven of the true faith (ſaith <hi>Auſtine</hi>) where no tempeſt of troubleſome curioſity, or of falſe doctrine can either trouble us, or at leaſt drown us, and therefore let us be ſtrong in faith, and hold that which we have, as Chriſt exhorts the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel of <hi>Thyatira,</hi> let us hold ſtedfaſt that which we have received, and continue faſt and conſtant in the Doctrine that we have, which is the true and old Doctrine, and not new, as that of the Hereticks.</p>
            <p>For we may demand of the Hereticks and with good ground, as <hi>Optatus</hi> did of the <hi>Donatiſts;</hi> an account of the beginning of their Chair, to wit of their Doctrine, which like unto <hi>Jona's</hi> gourd came up in a night, and periſhed in a night; having taken their beginning and birth ſince few dayes. Now if they demand where is the beginning of our Chair, or Doctrine, we anſwer in the and from the ſending of the Apoſtles; if again they ask a teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thereof, we will produce the ſame Doctrine which the holy Scripture contains, which reſounds in our pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pits, which ſounded or rather thundred in the Chair of the Apoſtles: The antient Heathens believed and held, that the fountain <hi>Arethuſa</hi> which did ſpring out in <hi>Syracuſa</hi> in <hi>Sycilie,</hi> was the river <hi>Alpheus;</hi> by what argument could
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:135682:16"/>
they be perſwaded, that the ſame water which loſeth it ſelf in the ſea, or under the mediterranean ſea, could in ſo long a ſpace ſpring and riſe up from the Land of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reah,</hi> as far as <hi>Sycily;</hi> becauſe that thoſe things that were caſt into that river were found again by the means of the ſaid fountain in <hi>Syracuſa.</hi> Even ſo we affirm that our Chair or doctrine hath taken its beginning from the time of the Apoſtles, although it hath been mixed or ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed in the ſea of this unclean world, full of corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, of falſe Doctrine, and manners; becauſe it brings back unto us that precious pearl, carried away and as it were ingulphed into the bottome of the ſea, by the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er partly of error, partly of perſecutions, (but from the preſence of thoſe only unto whom God hath ſent the efficacy of error, becauſe they would not receive the love of truth, that thereby they might be ſaved) Conſider thou <hi>Jonas,</hi> the type of the body of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and therefore alſo of his Church, thou ſeeſt him ſwallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up by the Whale, thou ſeeſt him devoured, and thou haſt ſome reaſon to believe it; at the onely word, at the twinckling of the eye of the Lord, this monſter vomits out <hi>Jonah</hi> upon the dry land, a Herald ordained to go from thence to preach unto the <hi>Ninivites,</hi> to a people ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens from the Church; and doſt thou find it ſtrange that this poore Church, which Popery as it were ſwallowed up, God willing it, having foretold it heretofore, mau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gre her power and malice, ſhe hath vomited it up again, and rendered it in our dayes, and for to preach the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel more gloriouſly, yea and that to our ſelves? So then we bring that which the Apoſtles have brought, have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered unto us, and have taught us; and therefore let us retain and maintain theſe Doctrines.</p>
            <p>And let us reject all falſe irregular and erroneous do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, which have too much the vogue and ſway in theſe Countreys. For <hi>England</hi> that was heretofore a Paradiſe, even as the Garden of the Lord, is alas become a <hi>Bochim,</hi> a valley of tears, an <hi>Aceldama,</hi> a field of blood, a <hi>Golgo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tha and Mount of Calvary,</hi> a Charnel of skulls, a common
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:135682:16"/>
ſinke and ſewer of all ſorts of Hereſies, and that there are here among us as many or more ſects and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions than there are among all the reformed Churches in <hi>Europe.</hi> There is a place near <hi>London,</hi> named <hi>the Iſle of dogs,</hi> but alas how many kinds of dogs are there in this Iſland of <hi>England.</hi> The ſacred Scripture compares divers kinds of perſons to dogs; the<note n="a" place="margin">Mat. 7.6.</note> 
               <hi>prophane perſons,</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Phil. 3.2.</note> 
               <hi>the Schiſmaticks,</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Iſa. 56.10</note> 
               <hi>mercenary Paſtors,</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Pſ. 22.17.</note> 
               <hi>the perſecutors, the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates;</hi> and eſpecially thoſe may be called dogs, that do bark againſt the Deity of God, or the Trinity of perſons,<note n="e" place="margin">2 Pet. 2.22.</note> as <hi>Arrius, Sabellian, Servetus, Socinus,</hi> and other blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Hereticks. Such an one was <hi>Lucian,</hi> a dog in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, who for his impiety was devoured by dogs. Such an one was <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtata, who being ſtruck with an unknown dart, caſted up his blood with his hand to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards heaven, crying aloud, <hi>Thou haſt overcome O Galile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, thou haſt overcome.</hi> The Arminians, and Socinians do agree together in many errors, that a man may ſay of them as of old, as of <hi>Plato</hi> and of <hi>Philo;</hi> either <hi>Philo doth Plato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſe,</hi> or <hi>Plato doth Philoniſe:</hi> So either the <hi>Arminians do Socinianiſe,</hi> or the <hi>Socinians do Arminianiſe</hi> in divers points, as concerning Predeſtination, original Sin, the unperſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of Saints touching the kingdom of Chriſt, univerſal grace, the Sacrament of Baptiſme, &amp; of the holy Supper of the Lord, and divers other things, &amp; among other points concerning the Son of God; ſaving, that the Son of God cannot rightfully &amp; truly be called Jehovah, God of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and by himſelf, that the arguments taken from the works of the creation, from the attributes of eternity, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the name of Jehovah, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are not ſufficient to prove the Deity of the Son of God; that Chriſt is named the Son of God in reſpect of his marvellous conception, his anoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, his reſurrection, aſcention, &amp; his ſitting at the right hand of God; &amp; is it not that which the Catechiſm of the Socinian Churches in <hi>Poland,</hi> and in <hi>Lithuania</hi> doth teach; affirming that there is but the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who is the only true God; that that man Jeſus of <hi>Nazareth,</hi> born of the Virgin is not God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> A book full
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:135682:17"/>
full of blafhemies againſt the ſon of God: a book that hath been reimprinted in <hi>England,</hi> without the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the ſuperior powers. A book which deſerues to be burnt) and it is ſaid it hath been) the Printers and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therers thereof worthy to be puniſhed, <hi>but O Lord how long?</hi> we read a notable example in the Eccleſiaſticall hiſtory. <hi>Amphilochius,</hi> an orthodox Biſhop in <hi>Licaonia,</hi> made a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt unto the Emperour <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> to be pleaſed to make a decree for the baniſhment of the Arrians out of his Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, but the Emperours rejected it, as an unjuſt and cruell requeſt; and which could not be executed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out danger. Now the Biſhop thought on a way how the Emperour might be moved to conſent to his requeſt He came one day with other Biſhops to the imperiall Court,<note place="margin">Theodor l. <hi>5</hi> c. <hi>16.</hi>
               </note> at the time that the Emperour <hi>Theodoſius</hi> ſat on his throne and <hi>Arcadius</hi> his ſon ſitting on his ſide, newly deſigned Emperour with him to congratulate them; which the Biſhops did and did congratulate both the Emperour and his ſon <hi>Arcadius,</hi> but <hi>Amphilochius</hi> did bow to the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> with all reverence and humility, but he did it not to his ſon <hi>Arcadius;</hi> the Emperour thought he did not do reverence to his ſon, either becauſe he ſaw him not, or by forgetfulneſſe; ſhews him his ſon, and adviſeth him to ſalute and honour him; but <hi>Amphilo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chius</hi> told him, <hi>He that honours the Father honoureth the ſon;</hi> the Emperour taking this act, this fact to heart, with a kind of indignation replyed unto him, <hi>He that diſhonour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Son diſhonoureth the Father;</hi> and commands thoſe about him to cauſe him to avoid the Court. <hi>Amphilochius</hi> having that which he deſired to attain unto his aim and end, cryed out, O Emperour doeſt thou take ſo to heart the contempt of thy ſonne? doſt thou think that in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhonouring thy ſon, I diſhonour thee? and doſt thou not think, that in diſhonouring the ſon of God, thou doſt not diſhonor God the Father? remember that God hates thoſe that diſhonor his Son: doth he not ſay<note n="f" place="margin">Joſh. 5.23.</note> 
               <hi>that all men ſhould honor the Son even as they honor the Father; he that honoreth not the Son honoreth not the Father which hath ſent him.</hi> The Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror was ſo much moved with this anſwer, admiring the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:135682:17"/>
wiſe boldnes of the old man, that he deſcended his throne, embraced the Biſhop, confeſſed he had told the truth, asked of him pardon, and made an Edict, baniſhing the Arrians out of his Empire: And <hi>certes</hi> Saint <hi>John</hi> ſaith,<note n="g" place="margin">1 <hi>John</hi> 2.23.</note> 
               <hi>Whoſoever denyeth the Son the, ſame hath not the Father; but he that acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth the Son, hath the Father alſo.</hi> Whoſoever therefore preacheth another Goſpel, another Jeſus, another Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, is accurſed; and <hi>if any man love not the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, let him be Anathema Maranatha.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.22. O that theſe Blaſphemers that ſin againſt God the Father, in ſinning againſt God the Son, either in regard of his perſon, or of his divine or humane nature, or of his offices, were ſuppreſſed in <hi>England:</hi> For how can we be ſaid to honour God the Father, if we permit that God the Son be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhonoured?</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Miniſters of the Goſpel ought and are to preach the Goſpel, not onely in regard of the Doctrine, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in reſpect of a holy converſation of life; edifying the Church of God, as well with the one hand as with the other; by the preaching of the word, and by good ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample. For otherwiſe the Paſtor will ruine the Church of God, more by his bad life, than he will edifie it by his wholeſome Doctrine; He will deſtroy that which he hath built, and will pluck up with one hand, that which he hath planted with the other; for the people look as much or more to his life and converſation, than to his preaching. He that preacheth well, and lives ill, is like the ſtatue of <hi>Mercury,</hi> who ſhews the way unto others, but doth not bow one ſtep; he reſembles the Scribes and Phariſees, that ſent the wiſe men of the Eaſt, that came to adore Jeſus Chriſt to <hi>Bethlehem,</hi> but ſtirred not from their houſes; they are like unto the Comedian, who cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with a loud voice, O heaven, ſhewed with his finger the earth, which the principall Magiſtrate beholding, could not fit longer in his place, but roſe and withdrew himſelf from the company in a fury, ſaying, this man hath made a ſoleciſme with his hand. So they that have Heaven at their tongues end, and the earth at their fingers end,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:135682:18"/>
ſpeak falſe and bad Divinity, whereas they might avoid ſuch an incongruous irregularity, and make a congrui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty between the tongue and the hand, if they did as they ſpeak, and lived as they preach. They are like to thoſe that built the Ark of <hi>Noah,</hi> but did not enter into it, and were not ſaved; ſo that thoſe who build the Church of God by their preaching, but are not of the Church by faith, which worketh by good deeds, ſhall not be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. They will ſay in the laſt day of Judgement to Jeſus Chriſt the Soveraign Judge,<note n="i" place="margin">Mat. 7.22, 23</note> 
               <hi>Lord, Lord, have we not prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſied in thy name, and in thy name done many wonderfull works?</hi> but the Judge will ſay unto them, <hi>I never knew you, depart from me ye that work iniquity</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Pſal. 50.16, 18.</note> 
               <note n="k" place="margin">Pſ. 50, 16, 18</note> 
               <hi>What haſt thou to do to declare my ſtatutes? or that thou ſhouldeſt take my Covenant in thy mouth? ſeeing when thou ſaweſt a thief, thou conſendeſt with him, and haſt been partaker with adulterers. Origen</hi> being excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated, for offering Incenſe on the altar, and ſo denying covertly Jeſus Chriſt, requeſted by ſome to expound un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the people a a paſſage of Scripture, fell by Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence on theſe 16, 17, 18 verſes of this 50. Pſalm; ſhut up the book, not able, not willing to expound that place, and wept, and all the people wept with him.<note n="l" place="margin">Rom. 2.21, 22 23, 24.</note> 
               <hi>Thou which teacheſt another, teacheſt thou not thy ſelf? thou that preacheſt a man ſhould not ſteal, doeſt thou ſteal? thou that ſayeſt a man ſhould not commit adultery, doeſt thou commit adultery? thou that abhoreſt Idols, doeſt thou commit Sacriledge? thou that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt thy boaſt of the Law through breaking the Law, diſhonoureſt thou God? for the name of the Lord is blaſphemed amomg the Gentiles through you.</hi> And therefore let us endeavour to marry our preaching with our life, leſt that by any means having preached to others, we our ſelves ſhould be caſt away and reprobates, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.27. Let us build the Church of God with the one and the other hand;<note n="m" place="margin">1 Tim. 4-13. 12.14.</note> 
               <hi>Let us give attendance to reading, to exhortation, to Doctrine, and be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo patterns of the believers, in word, in converſation, in charity, in ſpirit in faith, in purity,</hi> and that in conſideration <hi>of the laying on of the hands of the Presbytery,</hi> as it is in the 19. verſe of that ſame Chapter.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:135682:18"/>We intend not to diſcourſe here of the Impoſition, or of the laying on of the hands upon <hi>the ſacrifices,</hi> upon <hi>particular perſons in bleſſing them, or in healing them,</hi> and ſuch like things. But we ſay that the Impoſition or the laying on of the hands, is not a naked ceremony (as ſome ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe) as if it were of no efficacy; or on the other ſide, as if it did imprint an indelible character, which cannot be blotted out, (as the Papiſts ſay) or in breathing on per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons as the Biſhops do, and ſaying to them <hi>Receive ye the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> they received the Holy Ghoſt; as Chriſt in breathing on the Apoſtles, and ſaying, Receive ye the Holy Ghoſt, they received the Holy Ghoſt; or as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles in laying the hands on ſome who received the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary gift of the Holy Ghoſt, as it was in the time of the Primitive Church, when God did inrich his Church with that miraculous gift, when thoſe that had received the Impoſition of hands, did ſpeak ſtrange lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> No ſuch matter; but the laying on of the hands, which we that are Miniſters have received, and which our dear brother here preſent is to receive; doth ſignifie other things: For it ſignifies that the Miniſter is not ſent by himſelf, no man impoſeth hands on himſelf, <hi>Aaron</hi> himſelf hath been choſen;<note n="n" place="margin">Heb. 5.4.</note> 
               <hi>For no man taketh this Honour unto himſelf, but he that is called of God as was</hi> Aaron; <hi>So alſo Chriſt glorified not himſelf,</hi> but was called, and truly,<note n="o" place="margin">Rom. 10.17, 14, 15.</note> 
               <hi>Faith cometh by hearing, and hearing by the word of God, how ſhall they believe in him of whom they have not heard? and how ſhall they hear without a Preacher? and how ſhall they preach, except they be ſent.</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">Jer. 23.21.</note> 
               <hi>I have not ſent theſe Prophets, yet they ran, I have not ſpoken to them, yet they propheſied.</hi> The laying on of hands therefore ſignifies a ſending: <hi>The Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt ſaid</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">Acts 13.2, 3.</note> 
               <hi>ſeparate me</hi> Barnabas <hi>and</hi> Saul, <hi>for the work whereunto I have called them; and when they had faſted and prayed, and laid their hands on them, they ſent them away.</hi> So Moſes<note n="r" place="margin">Num. 27.22, 23.</note> 
               <hi>laid his hands upon his ſervant and ſucceſſour</hi> Joſhua <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all the Congregation, and gave him a charge as the Lord com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded him;</hi> Beſides it ſignifies the power and authority given unto him to preach, that receives the laying on of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:135682:19"/>
hands, authority according to the power that is given by Jeſus Chriſt, not to deſtruction but to edification; the laying on of the hands doth alſo ſignifie, that <hi>every good gift, and every perfect gift is from above, and cometh down from the Father of lights,</hi> Jam. 1.17. that God gives neceſſary and convenient gifts to the diſcharge of the Miniſter in his Miniſtry, <hi>Chriſt aſcended far above all heavens, that he might fill all things, and he gave ſome Apoſtles, and ſome Prophets, and ſome Evangeliſts, and ſome Paſtors and Teachers, &amp;c.</hi> The laying on of the hands therefore doth ſhew that God go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verns the Miniſtry, and guides his Miniſters by his hand, and his Church by the hand of his Miniſters.<note n="t" place="margin">Pſ. 77.20.</note> 
               <hi>Thou led<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt thy people like a flock by the hand of</hi> Moſes <hi>and</hi> Aaron. It declares the hand of God and his help, that he will be with his ſervants in all things and every where, will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve them in all dangers, and againſt all kind of evils. <note n="u" place="margin">1 Kin. 18 46.</note> 
               <hi>The hand of the Lord was on Elijah, he girded up his loins, and ran before</hi> Ahab <hi>to the entrance of</hi> Jezreel. In a word the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of hands ſignifies, that the Miniſter who is ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of God, is aſſured of his calling, is not for himſelf, but for God and his Church; and that the Miniſter ought to preach, and there is a neceſſity laid on him: and therefore he ought to take care, look diligently to his Commiſſion, for his office and Commiſſion is great and heavy, and hath need to pray to God to bleſſe him in his calling and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
            <p>On the other ſide, the laying on of the hands doth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the hand of God to be heavy on him, not for good, but for evil, if he doth not his duty. For as on the one ſide God ſaith,<note n="x" place="margin">Ezech. 33 9.8.</note> 
               <hi>Son of man if thou warn the wicked of his way to turn from it, if he do not turn from his way, he ſhall die in his iniquity; but thou haſt delivered thy ſoul; but if thou doeſt not ſpeak to warn the wicked from his way, that wicked man ſhall die in his iniquity, but his blood will I require at thine hand;</hi> and ſo wo unto us, if we preach not the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>And therefore the laying on of the hands doth admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh us, that as on the one ſide<note n="y" place="margin">1 Tim. 5.22.</note> 
               <hi>we lay hands ſuddenly on no man;</hi> ſo on the other ſide,<note n="z" place="margin">1 Tim. 4.14.</note> 
               <hi>we neglect not the gift that is in
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:135682:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
us, which was given by propheſie, with the laying on of the hands of the Presbytery.</hi> And<note n="a" place="margin">2 Tim. 1.6.</note> 
               <hi>Let us ſtir up the gift of God which is in us, by the putting on of hands.</hi> Let us hearken to that which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith to <hi>Archippus,</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Col 4.17</note> 
               <hi>Take heed to the Miniſtry which thou haſt received in the Lord, that thou fulfill it.</hi> Let us here the ſummons of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul; I</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">2 Tim. 4.1, 2.</note> 
               <hi>charge thee before God, and the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who ſhall judge the quick and the dead, at his appearance and his Kingdome, preach the word, be inſtant in ſeaſon, out of ſeaſon, reprove, rebuke, exhort, with all long ſuffering and doctrine.</hi> And elſewhere,<note n="d" place="margin">1 Tim. 5.21.</note> 
               <hi>I charge thee before God, and the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and the elect angels, that thou obſerve theſe things, without preferring one before ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, doing nothing by partiality.</hi> And again,<note n="e" place="margin">1 Tim. 6.13, 19.</note> 
               <hi>I give thee charge in the ſight of God, who quickeneth all things, and before Jeſus Chriſt, who before</hi> Pontius Pilate <hi>witneſſed a good confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, that thou keed this Commandement without ſpot, unrebuke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, untill the appearing of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt</hi> And that thou fleeſt<note n="f" place="margin">1 Tim. 6.10.</note> 
               <hi>Avarice the root of all evil.</hi> Avarice which <hi>Bernard</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſents, drawn by a Chariot with four wheels of vices; The firſt is <hi>faint heartedneſſe;</hi> The ſecond <hi>Inhumanity;</hi> The third, <hi>the contempt of God;</hi> The fourth, <hi>the forgetfulneſſe of death:</hi> this Chariot is drawn by two horſes coupled to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, the one <hi>forcible taking,</hi> the other <hi>force to retain things taken;</hi> the Coachman that guides this Chariot and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands it, is <hi>Covetouſneſſe or the love of money,</hi> who guiding the covetous man in ſuch a dangerous Coach, and with ſuch furious horſes, leads him out of the true way, makes him to erre from the faith, to fall into temptation and ſnares, and doth plunge him into deſtruction and perdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as the Apoſtle tells us in the 9. and 10. verſes of this ſixth Chapter: Therefore he doth exhort his diſciple <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothie</hi> in the 11. verſe, <hi>But thou O man of God flee theſe things, and follow after righteouſneſſe, godlineſſe, faith, love, patience, meekneſſe;</hi> as thou art, and as much as thou art a man of God, not onely in regard of the Creation, and of redemption, but more particularly in regard of thy vocation, a man of God, a Miniſter of the word of God. Which place of Scripture we expounded unto you in a
<pb facs="tcp:135682:20"/>
Sermon laſt <hi>Wedneſday,</hi> as a preparative and forerunner to this action; declaring what the Miniſter muſt flee, what he muſt follow after, before God and before men.</p>
            <p n="3">3. We that are Miniſters muſt learn that to preach the Goſpel well, and render our preaching fruitfull and of efficacy, we ought to be united together.<note n="g" place="margin">Pſal. 133.1, 2</note> 
               <hi>Behold how good and how pleaſant it is for brethren to dwell together in unity, it is like precious ointment upon the head of</hi> Aaron (when he was ordained and conſecrated an high Prieſt) <hi>that ran down upon the beard, even</hi> Aarons <hi>beard, that went down to the skirts of his garments.</hi> But alas, Satan to hinder the courſe and progreſſe of the Miniſtry, doth caſt the apple of diſcord between the Apoſtles themſelves, and between the Miniſters of the Goſpel alſo, One while for prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency,<note n="h" place="margin">Luke 22, 29.</note> 
               <hi>There was a ſtrife among the Apoſtles, which of them ſhould be accounted the greateſt.</hi> Another while for a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence concerning a third perſon, as between <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas,</hi> concerning <hi>John</hi> ſurnamed <hi>Mark;</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Acts 15.37, 38, 39, 40, 41.</note> Barnabas <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined to take with them</hi> Mark, <hi>but</hi> Paul <hi>thought it not good to take him with them; and the contention was ſo ſharp between them that they departed aſunder one from the other. So</hi> Barna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bas <hi>took</hi> Mark <hi>and ſailed unto</hi> Cyprus; <hi>but</hi> Paul <hi>choſe</hi> Silas <hi>and departed, being recommended by the brethren unto the grace of God, and he went through</hi> Syria <hi>and</hi> Cilicia <hi>confirming the Churches.</hi> Sometimes for the ſmall reſpect which one bears another, and by falſe reports. We read that there was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity between <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> and <hi>Severian,</hi> Biſhops; <hi>Serapion</hi> who wedded the quarrell of <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> paſſed by <hi>Seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian</hi> and did not ſalute him, <hi>Severian</hi> provoked with the little reſpect <hi>Serapion</hi> ſhewed him, gives way to his paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,<note place="margin">Socrates Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory.</note> and ſaid, <hi>If</hi> Serapion <hi>die a Chriſtian, Chriſt was not made man. Serapion</hi> reports the words of <hi>Severian</hi> at half and omits the firſt part of the Sentence, and tells <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome,</hi> that <hi>Severian</hi> maintained that Chriſt was not made man; thereupon <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> chaſeth <hi>Severian</hi> out of the City, the Empreſſe <hi>Eudoxia</hi> puts her ſelf between theſe two Biſhops, and endeavours to appeaſe the chol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> and brings her ſon <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> who
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:135682:20"/>
falls at Chryſoſtoms feet, to obtaine by intreatie a reconciliation, which by much adoe he compaſſed. If there had been no contention between theſe two Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, this had not happened; If Serapion who was Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtoms friend, had prevented Severian with honour, as the<note n="k" place="margin">Phil. 2.3.</note> Apoſtle exhorts; or at leaſt had given him the hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our that was due to him, and in Lowlineſſe of mind had eſteemed him better then himſelf; Severian had not ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered ſuch terible and unchriſtian words; if Serapion had not made a falſe report to Chryſoſtom concerning Seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian; and if Chryſoſtom had not been ſo light of beleef, but had examined both the one and the other party, and had reſerved one eare for the other party as Alexander the great did, he had not expelled Severian. Hence we ſee what diviſions among Paſtours can do; it is neceſſary that Paſtours<note n="l" place="margin">Gal. 6.2.</note> bear with one another burdens, that is, to ſay to beare with the infirmityes of one another, <hi>and ſo fulfill the Law of Chriſt,</hi> to ſupport them, redreſſe <hi>and reſtore them with the ſpirit of</hi> meekneſſe. In the time of the reformation of the Church of God; God ſtirred up two excellent and eminent perſons but of contrary conſtitutions and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſitions, Luther, and Melancton, Luther was hot, Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cton cold, Luther was of a cholerick inclination, but Melancton was of a temperat and ſweet diſpoſition, Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was couragious and bold, Melancton was timorous, Luther was as oyle and fire to warme his coldneſſe, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancton was as water to temper the heat of Luther, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancton was as a bridle to Luther, Luther was as a ſpurre to Melancton: by theſe means ſo contrary, and tones ſo diverſe, there was by Gods providence a holy harmony and faire coreſpondence between theſe two great inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God, and reſtorers of Gods Church, being hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily joyned together, and bearing with one anothers in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities. But if enmities continue between Paſtours, and that there is an apparent danger of a ſchiſme by their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions; Let us obſerve what Conſtantine the great Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour did, who having received divers letters from the Biſhops full of defamatory invectives of the one againſt
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:135682:21"/>
the others, and ſeeing that the Biſhops were more incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to wrangle one with another, than carefull to unite themſelves, and fight againſt the errour of <hi>Arrius.</hi> He caſt all their papers into the fire, without reading any of them, exhorting them to a mutuall peace, and brother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly concord one with another; and therefore let the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the word of God preach the word of God purely, let them live holily, let them love one another cordially; O then they will edifie the Church of God more and more; and having finiſhed their courſe, they ſhall receive their Crown of glory, <hi>Enter ye faithfull ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants into the joy of your Lord;</hi> and as they have been<note n="m" place="margin">Rev. 1.20.</note> 
               <hi>ſtars in Chriſts right hand,</hi> in the ſphere of this militant Church, <note n="n" place="margin">Dan. 12.3</note> 
               <hi>having turned many to righteouſneſſe; they ſhall ſhine as the brightneſſe of the firmament, and as the ſtarres for ever and ever,</hi> in the ſphere of the Triumphant Church in heaven;<note n="o" place="margin">Rev. 22.9. &amp; 20.</note> 
               <hi>as they are fellow ſervants with the angels, yea ſtiled angels here on earth,</hi> they ſhall be like the angels in glory in heaven.</p>
            <p>Now as we that are Miniſters have heard our leſſon, ye alſo (my brethren) have here your leſſon too; for if wo is unto Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> and unto the Miniſters of Gods word, if they preach not the Goſpel; it followeth that wo is unto the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> and unto you, if they hear not, if you hear not the preaching of the Goſpel; for if a neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity is laid upon Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> and upon P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſtors to preach; there is alſo a neceſſity laid upon the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the people of God to hear the Goſpel. It is that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity whereof Chriſt Jeſus ſpeaks,<note n="p" place="margin">Luke 10.41, 42.</note> Martha, Martha, <hi>thou art carefull and troubled about many things, but one thing is needfull, and</hi> Mary <hi>hath choſen that good part, which ſhall not be taken away from her.</hi> He ſpeaks of the neceſſity of the word of God,<note n="q" place="margin">Rom. 10.17.</note> 
               <hi>For faith cometh by hearing, and hearing by the word of God,</hi> and as he is of God that preacheth the word of God,<note n="r" place="margin">John 8.47.</note> 
               <hi>So he is of God that heareth Gods word.</hi> The ſame God that requires of the one the preaching, requires of the other the hearing; and therefore the ſame curſe that is pronounced and threatned againſt dumb Paſtors, is pronounced againſt deaf hearers. Wo unto them that
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:135682:21"/>
preach not the Goſpel, but alſo<note n="ſ" place="margin">Mar. 11.23.</note> 
               <hi>thou Capernaum, which art exalted unto heaven, thou ſhalt be brought to hell; for if the mighty works which have been done in thee, had been done in</hi> So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome <hi>it would have remained untill this day.</hi> In <hi>Sodome,</hi> there was a <hi>Lot,</hi> in <hi>Capernaum</hi> a Jeſus; <hi>Lot</hi> was a man, Chriſt God and man; <hi>Lot</hi> was a ſinner, Chriſt innocent; <hi>Lot</hi> did no miracles among the Sodomites, Chriſt did mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles in <hi>Capernaum; Sodom</hi> ſaw not any Judgements on <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> as <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> ſaw thoſe fearfull and terrible Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments on <hi>Sodom,</hi> written in characters from heaven of fire and Brimſtone; ſo that one might, as it were, read them in running, The Lake <hi>Aſphaltites</hi> or dead ſea, is a fearfull teſtimony of Gods wrath upon them; and therefore <hi>it ſhall be more tolerable for the land of</hi> Sodom <hi>in the day of Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment than for them;</hi>
               <note place="margin">verſe 29.</note> according to that the Apoſtle teacheth us,<note n="t" place="margin">Heb. 2.2, 3</note> 
               <hi>That if the word ſpoken by angels was ſtedfaſt, and every tranſgreſſion and diſobedience received a juſt recompence of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward; how ſhall we eſcape if we neglect ſo great ſalvation, which at the firſt began to be ſpoken by the Lord, was confirmed unto us by them that heard him.</hi> And therefore a neceſſity is laid up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the people of God to hear his holy word.</p>
            <p>The <hi>ſecond duty</hi> of Gods people is, to pray for their Paſtors, the people think that it is the Paſtors Office, and duty to pray for them, and that is true, for the Miniſter of God is Gods mouth to the People, and the peoples mouth to God; it is he that makes interceſſion between God and the people, <q>
                  <note n="u" place="margin">1 Sam. 12 23.</note> God forbid that I ſhould ſin a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Lord, in ceaſing to pray for you,</q> ſaith <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel;</hi> and truly <hi>Moſes</hi> interceding for the Jews; <hi>Samuel</hi> and <hi>Daniel</hi> in like manner, have been powerfull interceſſors, and their prayers have been of great force towards God, for the good of the people of God, in the name and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion of the Meſſias to come, namely Jeſus Chriſt: but you muſt know it is alſo the duty of the people to pray for their Paſtors and teachers; for ſo great an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> had need of the prayers of the Church, and ſaid, <hi>Pray for me that the door of utterance may be given unto me, that I may ſpeak boldly, to make known the myſtery of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:135682:22"/>
Eph.</hi> 6.19. and <q>and you alſo helping together by prayer for us, that for the gift beſtowed upon us, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q> 2 Cor. 1.11. how much more we that are inferiours to ſo great an Apoſtle, have need of your prayers.<note n="x" place="margin">Acts 12.5.</note> 
               <hi>Prayer was made without ceaſing of the Church unto God for</hi> Peter. And <hi>certes</hi> we fear, that by reaſon of the want of the prayes of Gods people for their Paſtors, God takes away ſometimes the Miniſters of his holy word; as God hath taken away to himſelf out of your Church three Paſtors in nine moneths.<note place="margin">Mr. Marmet, Mr. Mary, Mr. Primroſe, Anno <hi>1642.</hi>
               </note> And God ſuffers ſometimes Miniſters to fall into ſtrange and irregular opinions, into hereſies, or into ſome ſcandalous ſin, becauſe the Church prayeth not with that zeal and fervour for their Paſtors as they ought: if therefore you deſire that God continue his Miniſtry among you, and preſerve your Miniſters, it behoves you to pray to God for your Miniſters; for that is their deſire: So the Martyrs were accuſtomed to cloſe and finiſh their Epiſtles to their friends, with theſe words, <hi>Pray, Pray, Pray for us, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, Gods people ought to be united, and not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided; for where the ſpirit of diviſion is, there cannot be the ſpirit of prayer nor of concord. Now as the amity and concord of Paſtors one with another, and of Paſtors with the people, is of great profit; ſo their diviſion is of a dangerous conſequence; the chiefs and principalls, diſagreeing have alwayes their adherents. The Apoſtle condemnes theſe diviſions among the <hi>Corinthians.</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">1 Cor. 1.12.</note> 
               <q>It hath been declared unto me of you, that there are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions among you; for every one of you ſaith, I am of <hi>Paul,</hi> and I of <hi>Apollo,</hi> and I of <hi>Cephas,</hi> and I of Chriſt, Is Chriſt divided? is <hi>Paul</hi> crucified for you? or were you baptiſed in the name of <hi>Paul.</hi>
                  <note n="z" place="margin">1 Cor. 3.3, 5.</note> There is among you envying and ſtrife, and diviſions, are ye not carnal, and walk as men? who is <hi>Paul?</hi> who is <hi>Apollo,</hi> but mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters by whom ye believed?</q> By this he gives us to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand that there is nothing more dangerous and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious, than the diviſion among the people, concerning Paſtors; eſpecially when there is more regard to one mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:135682:22"/>
than to another, and ſome are admirers, yea idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of their perſons; as the Jews preferred <hi>Abraham, Jacob, Moſes,</hi> and eſteemed them above <hi>Chriſt,</hi> an inſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portable blaſphemy: <hi>Luther, Calvin,</hi> and others have been too much eſteemed, and preferred before other Miniſters. The report is, that there was a man in <hi>Geneva</hi> that made ſo much eſteem of <hi>Calvin,</hi> that he ſaid, if Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſhould come down from heaven, and preach at the ſame time that <hi>Calvin</hi> preached, he would rather hear <hi>Calvin</hi> then <hi>Paul.</hi> O let us not be admirers and adorers of perſons; it is God that gives divers gifts unto Paſtors by the ſame ſpirit. Such an one will expound the Text wondrous well, and cite to the purpoſe the Paſſages of the ſacred Scripture; another will apply well; another will be an excellent and eloquent Orator. Such an one will be a great diſputer of controverſies, Another as a <hi>Boanerges</hi> will thunder forth Judgements of God; Another will be a <hi>Barnabas</hi> admirable in his conſolations; This man will be patheticall in his uſes; That man will be admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable in his prayers. Another will be excellent in Conſiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and in Councell, and it may be there will be ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that hath not theſe and the like gifts, which will be more humble than all the reſt. There is not one among a thouſand that hath all theſe gifts together, as <hi>Elihu</hi> ſaid to <hi>Job,</hi> 
               <q>if there be a meſſenger with him, one among a thouſand, to ſhew to man his uprightneſſe,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 4.1.</note> 
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Job</hi> 33.23.</bibl>
               </q> Therefore let us eſteem them all, <q>and ſo account of them as of the Miniſters of Chriſt, and ſtewards of the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of God, and of the divers gifts o his Spirit, and that there be no diviſions among us, which ruines and turns upſided down the Church of God, as ſad experience teacheth us.</q> That as the <hi>Tythean</hi> ſtone, though a great one, yet as long as it is whole ſwims, but being broken in pieces ſinks to the bottome. So the Church of God united, ſubſiſts; but divided ſinks down; ſure no houſe, no city, no Church, no Kingdome being divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded can ſtand. And therefore if we deſire the proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Gods Church, the good of this Church, be united
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:135682:23"/>
together,<note n="a" place="margin">Acts 2.1.</note> 
               <hi>be all with one accord in one place, fall not out by the way,</hi> Gen. 45.24. <hi>If</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Phil. 2.1, 2, 3.</note> 
               <hi>therefore there be any conſolation in Chriſt, if any comfort of love, if any fellowſhip of the Spirit, if any bowels and mercies, fulfill ye my joy, ſaith Saint</hi> Paul, <hi>that ye be like minded, having the ſame love, being of one accord, of of one mind, let nothing be done through ſtrife, vain glory;</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Eph. 4.3, 4, 5, 6.</note> 
               <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devouring to keep the unity of the Spirit in the bond of peace: there is one body and one ſpirit, ye are called in one hope of your calling, having one Lord, one faith, one baptiſme, one God and father of all, who is above all, and through all, and in you all,</hi> and one mother the Church.</p>
            <p>Now he who is is the Almighty God powerfull to confirm and ſtrengthen us, according to his Goſpel, and the preaching of Chriſt; fortifie us more and more in faith, and in the truth of his Goſpel, and brotherly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord and charity, make us firm and ſtable therein, that when Jeſus Chriſt ſhall come in his glory and Majeſty, pouring down the cataracts of his indignation upon the wicked, he may find us holding that which he hath ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhed us of, obſerving that which he hath taught us, doing that which he hath done, retaining his Goſpel till his coming; Then may we be aſſured that we ſhall be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in that laſt day; Paſtors and ſheep governed and gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in one ſheepfold, under the hook of that grand and Soveraign Shepherd of our ſouls Jeſus Chriſt, to be fed by him, received in his Kingdome and crowned with glory, there we ſhall live with the Patriarcks, the Prophets, the Apoſtles, with the angels, with the Saints, and with our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, to whom with the Father, and the Holy Ghoſt, be given all honour, glory, power, Majeſty, and dominion for ever and ever, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <head>The Sermon being finiſhed, the Miniſter ſpake unto the people ſaying,</head>
            <p>YE have heard (my brthren) that the brother <hi>John Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſta Stouppe,</hi> being choſen by the Conſiſtory of this Church, to be a Paſtor of this ſaid Church, hath undergone
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:135682:23"/>
the examination; wherein he hath made apparent his dexterity, both in his Latine Sermon <hi>ad Clerum,</hi> as alſo in anſwering unto the objections which have been made and propounded unto him, concerning the principall points of the Chriſtian Religion; ſo that he hath been judged capable to be admitted unto the Miniſtry; who having been publiſhed two ſucceeding Lords-dayes publickly in this Church, and having heard of no oppoſition on your part; we take your ſilence as an approbation of his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry among you; and therefore we will proceed unto his reception unto the Miniſtry. But firſt we will read unto you that which is written the 1. Epiſtle to <hi>Timothy,</hi> chap. 3 from the 1. verſe to the 7. verſe incluſively, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that the 1. chapter to <hi>Titus</hi> the 4. verſe to the 10. verſe excluſively; and you may read at your leaſure the 9. chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the 1. Epiſtle unto the <hi>Corinthians;</hi> then we will take a promiſe from our brother, and afterwards we will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to his ordination unto the Miniſtry.</p>
            <p>So having read that which is written to <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus,</hi> concerning the charge and duty of Paſtors of the Church of God. The Miniſter ſpake to Mr. <hi>Stouppe,</hi> ſaying,</p>
            <p>You <hi>John Baptiſta Stouppe</hi> do promiſe before God and his Church, that you will ſerve him faithfully in your miniſtry to the which you are called; preaching truly the word of God, to edifie the Church, and that you will not abuſe the Doctrine, to ſerve your carnall affections, or to pleaſe any man living; but that you will uſe it in a ſound conſcience to ſerve to his glory, and the benefit of his people: you do promiſe alſo that you will keep the Eccleſiaſticall ordinances, and the Diſcipline received in this Church; and as your charge is, admoniſh thoſe that fail, to acquit your ſelf faithfully, without giving any place to hatred, favour, vengeance, or any other carnall affection, and in general do that which belongs to a good and faithfull Miniſter: <hi>Item</hi> you promiſe to keep and maintain as far as lyeth in you, the good and preſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this eſtate, procure in what poſſible you can the peace and union thereof, and not to conſent any manner of way to that which may be contrary and hurtfull to it.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:135682:24"/>The brother Mr. <hi>Stouppe</hi> by his geſture ſignified his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, and anſwered, yea.</p>
            <p>The Miniſter ſaid to him, God give you the grace to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh your promiſe.</p>
            <p>The Miniſter being deſcended from the Pulpit (and the brother <hi>Stouppe</hi> kneeling on a cuſhion within the inclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure where Miniſters and Elders ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>) accompanied with Mr. <hi>Calendrin</hi> Miniſter of the Dutch Church of <hi>London,</hi> and with Mr. <hi>Ciſmer</hi> miniſter of the French Church of <hi>London;</hi> having all three their hands on his head, his back turned towards the people, and his face towards the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters. The miniſter made this prayer as followeth.</p>
            <q>
               <p>ALmighty God, heavenly Father, who after the fall of our firſt Parents was the firſt preacher of the Goſpel in Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe unto our ſaid Parents, and our Lord Jeſus Chriſt being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended from heaven on earth for our ſakes, honoured and ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the holy miniſtry in his own perſon, and aſcending up into hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to give gifts to man, he gave ſome Apoſtles, and ſome Prophets and ſome Evangeliſts, and ſome Paſtors and teachers for the perfecting of the Saints for the work of the Miniſtry, for the edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying of the body of Chriſt; ſeeing it hath pleaſed thee to call our dear brother, and thine humble ſervant, proſtrated here on his knees before thee, to be ordinated and ordained Miniſter of thy holy word We beſeech thee to give him ſufficient graces, that he may thereby acquit himſelf vertuouſly and duly of his charge in this his Miniſtry, and denounce the ſecret of thy Son, that he may manifeſt it as he ought; create in him a new heart, in changing his heart into another, as thou didſt unto <hi>Saul</hi> being anointed King transform him by the renewing of his mind, that he may prove what is that good, that acceptable that perfect wil of thine enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en his underſtanding from above, with the rayes and beams of thy divine light, warm him and fill him with the true zeal of thy glory, and ſincere intention to thy Service; open his lips, and his mouth ſhall ſet forth thy praiſe guide him in all truth, that be walk not deceitfully nor falſifie thy word but that he hold faſt the faithfull word, which is according to inſtruction, let him not have the ſpirit of fear and timerouſnes, but the ſpirit of ſtrength and of courage, let the word be given to him with a doore of utterance and with a
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:135682:24"/>
covenient boldneſſe, that he may ſpeak freely as he ought, and fear not thoſe that can kill the body and not the ſoul, but rather that he fear thee (O God) that canſt deſtroy body and ſoul in hell. Let the <hi>Tummims</hi> and <hi>Urims,</hi> to wit perfection and light be upon him; give him grace that in any part of his calling he be not moved, nor carried away with ambition or covetouſneſſe; but as a man of God, not as he is to thee, ſuch an one by creation or redemption, onely, but as he is a man of God, by this particular calling, he flee theſe things, and follow after righteouſneſſe, godlineſſe, faith, love, patience, meekneſſe; diſpel from him the deſires of the world, which may interlace in his thought, and traverſe his holy reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, permit not (O good God) that the world by his allurements and baits, or his own fleſh by its infirmities have the upper hand, but ſtrengthen him by thy holy Spirit, that he may be victorious in the midſt of aſſaults, by faith that may be his victory that over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cometh the world. Give him thy grace to preach thy holy word purely, to live holily and religiouſly, and marry his holy life with his preaching, that he ruine not that with one that which he builds with the other, but that he may be an example to the faithfull in word, in converſation, in charity, in ſpirit, in faith, in purity, leſt by any means having preached to others, he himſelf ſhould be a caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>away. Govern him by thy holy ſpirit, that he attribute nothing to himſelf, but to the vertue of thy holy ſpirit, and acknowledge that it is not <hi>Paul</hi> that planteth, nor <hi>Apollo</hi> that watereth, but it is thou O God that giveſt the increaſe; give him grace that he may have prudence in his guiding, efficacy in his preaching, that he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh the unruly, comfort thoſe that are of a low ſpirit, and feeble heart, chear up the weak ones, that he be of a mild ſpirit towards all; and that he walk in his calling as it is fitting to the glory of thy great name, to the advancement of the Kingdome of thy Son our Lord, to the edification and conſolation of this Church, and to the ſalvation of his own Soul, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <div type="part">
               <head>After the Prayer ended, the Miniſter added and ſaid, in ordaining and conſecrating him, the two other Miniſters, continuing their hands on his head with him.</head>
               <p>IN the name and by the authority of the Almighty God, the Father, the Son, and the Holy Ghoſt; at the requeſt of the Conſiſtory of this Church, and according to the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:135682:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Commiſſion and charge which hath been given us, and we have accepted of. We Miniſters of Gods word do inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute thee <hi>John Baptiſta Stouppe,</hi> do conſecrate thee, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm thee Miniſter of the word of God, in the Church of God, and particularly of this Church; we give thee power and authority, to preach the word of God, to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribute the Sacraments, to exerciſe the Eccleſiaſticall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline conformable to Gods word; and to do all the functions that appertain to the man of God, and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of Gods word.</p>
               <p>And to the end that God ratifie in heaven that which we do here on earth, we beſeech him <hi>who is the God of peace, who through the blood of the everlaſting covenant, hath brought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain from the dead that great Shepherd of the ſheep,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 13.20 21.</note> who is our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>make you perfect in every good work, to do his will, working in you that which is well pleaſing in his ſight, through Jeſus Chriſt, to whom be glory for ever, and ever Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Paranym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phi.</note>Then the two Miniſters brought back the Miniſter, new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ordained and confirmed to the ſeat of the Miniſters, who ſat between them both. And the Miniſter aſcended the Pulpit; made the ordinary prayer, but there where it concerned Paſtors, he interlaced a prayer for the Miniſter confirmed, and among other things concerning the laying on of the hands on his perſon. The prayer ended, he cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Pſalm 133. to be ſung, <hi>O how happy a thing it is, and joyfull for to ſee, brethren together faſt to hold, the band of amity, &amp;c.</hi> and that according to the ſubject, concerning the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecration of <hi>Aaron,</hi> and concord; then afterward he bleſſed the people in the preſcribed form, in the 6. chap. of <hi>Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, The Lord bleſſe thee and keep thee, the Lord make his face to ſhine upon thee, and be gracious unto thee &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Afterwards the Paſtours and Elders entred into the Conſiſtory, and as <hi>James, Cephas</hi> and <hi>John</hi> gave the right hand of fellowſhip to <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.9.</note> ſo the three Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors gave the right hand of fellowſhip to Mr. <hi>Stouppe</hi> their fellow brother, with convenient congratulations, and holy wiſhes; then the brethren Elders one after another, did the like unto him. So this Action ended to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment of the Church.</p>
            </div>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
